<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The lives and deaths of the holy apostles of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ together with the two evangelists St. Mark and St. Luke : as also, some other of our Saviours disciples containing an account of their travels, sayings, miracles, sufferings and martyrdoms / all collected from the best authors for public use and benefit.</title>
            <author>P. D.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 166 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 78 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37402</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D78</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27282</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09790746</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09790746</idno>
            <idno type="VID">44102</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A37402)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 44102)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1354:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The lives and deaths of the holy apostles of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ together with the two evangelists St. Mark and St. Luke : as also, some other of our Saviours disciples containing an account of their travels, sayings, miracles, sufferings and martyrdoms / all collected from the best authors for public use and benefit.</title>
                  <author>P. D.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 143 p. : ports.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Dorman Newman,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: P.D.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Biography.</term>
               <term>Apostles.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:44102:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>THE Lives &amp; Deaths Of the Holy APOSTLES Of Our <hi>Lord</hi> &amp; <hi>Saviour <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
                     </hi> Together With the Two Evangeliſts, SAINT <hi>Mark</hi> and <hi>Luke.</hi>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:44102:1"/>
            <p>THE Lives &amp; Deaths Of the Holy APOSTLES Of Our Lord and Saviour <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Together with the Two Evangeliſts, S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> 
               <hi>MARK</hi> and S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> 
               <hi>LUKE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As Alſo, Some other of our Saviours Diſciples: Containing An Account of Their Travels, Sayings, Miracles, Sufferings, and Martyrdoms.</p>
            <p>All Collected from the Beſt Authors, for Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Uſe and Benefit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Dorman Newman,</hi> at the <hi>Kings Armes</hi> in the <hi>Poultry,</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:44102:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:44102:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THou art here Preſented with the Lives of the Holy Apoſtles; Men, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ho as they were Honour'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith the higheſt Offices in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Church, ſo they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f higheſt Renown in the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hriſtian</hi> World, both for
<pb facs="tcp:44102:3"/>their Lives and Deaths. Great Subject, and a No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Study; in the managi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> whereof, I have glean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what I could meet wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that I thought was moſt m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terial for the Reader to kno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> That which firſt put me up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Writing it, was the Acce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tance the Book Intituled, <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Testament of the Twelve P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>triarks,</hi> found amongſt mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> men: But this, as the Autho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> are more Venerable amo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Christians,</hi> ſo I have pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſely omitted all things th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> might occaſion any Diſpu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:44102:3"/>concerning them. This Book being calculated as well for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light as profit; &amp; indeed it can be no ſmall pleaſure, to have ſo many great pieces of Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, (as you will find in this ſmall Book) brought to ſpeak <hi>Engliſh;</hi> whereby a common eye may look into Divine &amp; Ineſtimable Treaſure of the Wiſeſt and beſt Ages of the World. In theſe Lines, the Reader will ſee the firſt and pureſt Ages of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion, when Men were really what they pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be; when a ſolid
<pb facs="tcp:44102:4"/>Piety and Devotion, a ſtrict Temperance and Sobriety, a <hi>Catholick</hi> and unbounded Charity, an exemplary Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty &amp; Integrity; a great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence for every thing that was Divine and Sacred, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <hi>Christianity</hi> beautiful &amp; lovely to the World Here thou wilt ſee the Reaſons and Occaſions of the Feaſts and Faſts of the Church, and what made thoſe Primitive Times thrive. To provoke thy imitation, my buſineſs was to deliver this Work in that Form and Order, that I think
<pb facs="tcp:44102:4"/>it may not be unfitly ſtyled the Story of Stories; wherein you will find contrived in one continual Order of Hiſtorical Reading, thoſe Famous and Glorious Acts, which are contained in the Lives of theſe Holy Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>He that reads theſe great Saints Lives, will ſee the Grounds of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to be ſo noble and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, all its Laws ſo iuſt and rational, all its deſignes ſo Divine and Heavenly, that he cannot but conclude the Principles to be perfect: and
<pb facs="tcp:44102:5"/>conducive to the happineſs of Humane Nature, a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion ſo worthy of God, ſo Advantagious to Human Nature, built upon the ſtrongeſt evidence, cloathed with ſuch ſtrong and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful Arguments, that he will preſently be convinced of the Decency that reſides in it.</p>
            <p>And certainly, nothing can be of more efficacy to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade Chriſtians to, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage them in, a Pious, God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and Religious Life, Then the Conſiderations they
<pb facs="tcp:44102:5"/>may be able to make upon reading the Lives and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of theſe Holy Saints and Martyrs, when we reflect upon their extraordinary Self-denial, Piety, Charity, Juſtice, Moderation, and all other Vertues ſo Conſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the whole courſe of Their Apoſtleſhips.</p>
            <p>If to be Short will pleaſe thee, here is Brevity; If Change will pleaſe, here is Variety; If Profit will pleaſe, I dare ſay it ſhall be thy fault if thou be not the Better for it: May theſe Lines be as ſo
<pb facs="tcp:44102:6"/>many Sparks from Heaven collected thus together, which may not only afford Light to our Underſtandings, but Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine love to all ſincere Souls: That as it had a Heavenly heat in them, it may influence all the lovers of Devotion and Piety; is the hearty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of the Publiſher.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>P. D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:44102:6"/>
            <head>BOOKS Printed for, and Sold by <hi>Dorman Newman</hi> at the <hi>Kings-Armes</hi> in the <hi>Poultry.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>THe Hiſtory of the <hi>Seaven Wiſe Maſters.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Hiſtory of St. <hi>Patrick</hi> of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Lives and Deaths of the Holy Apoſtles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Hiſtory of <hi>Fortunatus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>Crown Garland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Poor Robins</hi> Preambulations.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Small Hiſtories.</head>
               <item>A Merry Book of All Fives.</item>
               <item>Croſſing of Proverbs.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Laurance Lazie.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Unfortunate Welſh-Man.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Venus Turtle Doves.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Unfortunate <hi>Jack.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Vinegar</hi> and <hi>Muſtard.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:44102:7"/>
The Hiſtory of <hi>Valantine</hi> and <hi>Orſon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Hiſtory of Fryer <hi>Bacon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Hiſtory of the Seven Champions of <hi>England.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>With moſt other, both Large and Small Hiſtories.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:44102:7"/>
            <head>The Life of S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> 
               <hi>PETER.</hi>
            </head>
            <figure>
               <p>
                  <hi>St</hi> PETER</p>
            </figure>
            <p>IN the Land of <hi>Paleſtine</hi> ſtood a Village call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Bethſaida,</hi> formerly an obſcure and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable place, belonging to the Tribe of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:44102:8"/>
               <hi>Nepthali,</hi> but lately re-edified, and greatly enlarged by <hi>Phillip</hi> the <hi>Tetrarch,</hi> and by him advanced to the Place and Dignity of a City, repleniſhed with many Inhabitants, and ſtrongly Fortified with Power and Strength, which <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> in honour of his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, called <hi>Julias.</hi> It was ſcituated upon the Sea of <hi>Galilee,</hi> and had a Wilderneſs upon the other ſide thence, called, <hi>The Deſert of <hi>Bethſaida.</hi>
               </hi> But for as great as its Splendor was at this time, late Travellers aſſures, that now it is become a moſt deſolate and contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible Village, conſiſting of a few Cottages of <hi>Moors</hi> and Wild <hi>Arabs:</hi> And later Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers have ſince aſſured us, that even theſe are dandled away into one poor Cottage at this day. So fatally does Sin undermine the greateſt and goodlieſt pleces; ſo heavily did our Saviours old Predict (one for their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the Goſpel) light on them.</p>
            <p>Next to the Honour that this place had by our Saviours preſence, who living moſt in theſe parts, did often reſort hither. It had nothing greater to recommend it to the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of Poſterity, then that (beſides ſome other of the Apoſtles) it was the Birth-place of St. <hi>Peter;</hi> a Perſon how inconſiderable ſoever in his private Fortunes, yet of great Note and Eminency, as one of the prime Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors of the Son of God, to whom both Sacred and Eccleſiaſtical Stories gives high
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:44102:8"/>and Eminent Elogies among the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>We are much in the dark as to the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar time of his Birth, no probable Foot-ſteps nor intimations of it being found in Antiquity; yet in the general, we may conclude him at leaſt, to have been about Ten Years Elder then his Maſter; his Marryed Condition and ſettled courſe of Life when he firſt came to Chriſt, and the great Authority and reſpect which the Gravity of his Perſon did procure him amongſt the reſt of the Apoſtles, with other ſuch Circumſtances, can ſpeak him no leſs: But for any thing more poſitive and particular in this matter, we cannot affirm for a certain truth, though one poſitively tells us, that he was Born three Years before the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Lord, and juſt Seventeen Years before the Incarnation.</p>
            <p>Being Circumciſed according to the rites of the <hi>Moſaick</hi> Law, the Name given him at his Circumciſion, was <hi>Simon,</hi> or <hi>Simeon;</hi> a Name common among the <hi>Jews,</hi> eſpecially in their latter times. This Name was afterward not aboliſhed by our Saviour, but additioned with the Title of <hi>Cephas,</hi> which in the <hi>Syri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ack,</hi> which was the Vulgar Language of the <hi>Jews</hi> at that time, did ſignifie a <hi>Stone,</hi> or <hi>Rock,</hi> was thence derived unto the <hi>Greek</hi> Word <hi>Petros,</hi> rendred in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Langu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age <hi>Peter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:44102:9"/>
His Father was <hi>Jonah,</hi> probably a Fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of <hi>Bethſaida;</hi> the Sacred Story taking no further notice of him, then by the bare mention of his Name. Brother he was to St. <hi>Andrew</hi> the Apoſtle, and there is ſome queſtion among the Ancients, which of the two was the Elder Brother; <hi>Epiphanius</hi> clearly adjudges it to St. <hi>Andrew:</hi> St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> upon the other hand, ſaith ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, That though <hi>Andrew</hi> came later into Life then <hi>Peter,</hi> yet he brought him firſt to the knowledge of the Goſpel. But however it was, it ſounds not a little to the honour of their Father, (as of <hi>Zebedee,</hi> alſo in the like caſe) that of but twelve Apoſtles, two of his Sons were taken into the number. In his Youth he was brought up to Fiſhing, which we may gueſs to have been the Staple Trade of <hi>Bethſaida,</hi> (which hence probably borrowed its Name) ſignifying an Houſe, or Habitation of Fiſhing, much advantaged herein by the Neighbourhood of the <hi>Lake</hi> of <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſareth</hi> (on whoſe Banks it ſtood) called alſo <hi>the Sea of <hi>Galilee,</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>the Sea of <hi>Tiberius,</hi>
               </hi> according to the Mode of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, wherein all confluences of Waters are called Seas. It was an hundred Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs in length, and forty in breadth; the Waters of it moſt clear, ſweet, and moſt fit to drink; ſtored with ſeveral ſorts of Fiſh,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:44102:9"/>and thoſe different both in kind and taſte, from thoſe in any other place.</p>
            <p>Here it was that St. <hi>Peter</hi> cloſly follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the exerciſe of his Calling, from whence it ſeems, he afterward removed to <hi>Caperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> probably upon his Marriage (at leaſt fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently reſided there) for there we meet with his Houſe, and there we find him paying Tribute: An Houſe, over which it is ſaid, that <hi>Heben</hi> the Mother of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> built a Temple in Honour of St. <hi>Peter.</hi> This place was advantageous for the managing of his Trade, ſtanding on the entrance of <hi>Jordan</hi> into the Sea of <hi>Galilee;</hi> and where he might as well reap the Fruits of an honeſt and induſtrious Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence. It's true, it was a mean and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile courſe of life; for beſides the great pains and labour it required, he was by it expoſed to the injuries of Wind and Weather, to the Storms of the Sea, the darkneſs and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtuouſneſs of the Night, and all to make a mean and very ſmall return; but mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is no Bar in Gods way: Nay; our Lord ſeems to caſt a peculiar Honour upon that Profeſſion; When afterwards calling him, and ſome others of the ſame Trade, from catching of Fiſh, to be Fiſhers of Men.</p>
            <p>And now to reflect a little upon the Wiſe and Admirable Methods of Divine Providence, it is Wonderful to behold it in its Methods, in Propagating the Chriſtian Faith in the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:44102:10"/>World; that ſuch low and mean Men ſhould be armed with ſuch Divine Power to the run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning down the Kingdom of Satan: The vile Apoſtate <hi>Julian</hi> thought this a reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Exception againſt the Prophets of the Old Teſtament, that they were a Company of Rude and Illiterate Men; but here lay the Wonder of it, that the firſt Preachers of the Goſpel ſhould be ſuch rude unlearned Men, and yet ſo ſuddenly, ſo powerfully, prevail Over the Learned World.</p>
            <p>We find not whether <hi>Peter,</hi> before his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Chriſt, was Ingraffed in any of the Sects at that time in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church; yet is it greatly probable, that he was One of the Diſciples of <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, for it is certain that his Brother <hi>Andrew</hi> was ſo; and we can hardly think theſe Two Brothers ſhould draw two contrary ways, or that he who was ſo ready to bring his Brother the early Tydings of the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> ſhould not be as ſolicitous to bring him under the Diſcipline and Influence of <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, the Day-Star that went before him. As alſo <hi>Peter</hi>'s forwardneſs and curioſity at the firſt news of Chriſt's appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to come to him and Converſe with him, ſhew that his Expectations had been awaken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſome light in this matter conveyed to him by the Preaching and Miniſtry of <hi>John.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>St. <hi>Peter</hi> was introduced into Chriſt's Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance
<pb facs="tcp:44102:10"/>by means of his Brother <hi>Andrew;</hi> at which time our Lord gave him the Title of <hi>Cephas.</hi> What paſſed further between them, and whether theſe two Brothers henceforward Perſonally attended our Saviours Motions in the number of his Diſciples, we cannot cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly determine; it ſeems probable that they ſtayed with him for ſome time till they were In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in the firſt Rudiments of his Doctrine, and by his leave departed home; for we may reaſonably ſuppoſe that our Lord being unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, at this time eſpecially, to Awaken the Iealouſie of the State by a Numerous Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, might diſmiſs his Diſciples for ſome time, and <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Andrew</hi> amongſt the reſt; who, hereupon, returned home to the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of their Calling, where they continued ſomewhat more than a Year; at which time our Lord came along one Morning where they had been all Night at their Work, but taught nothing; but at his deſire the Net be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing let down, there was a miraculous draught of Fiſh caught; whereupon <hi>Peter</hi> preſently leaving all, followed him: the firſt Way he went was to <hi>Capernaum,</hi> where Chriſt heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Peter</hi>'s Wifes Mother.</p>
            <p>Our Lord being to Elect ſome Peculiar Perſons as his Immediate Vicegerents up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth, withdrew himſelf over-Night to a ſolitary Mountain: early the next Morning
<pb facs="tcp:44102:11"/>his Diſciples came to him, out of whom he made Choice of Twelve to be his Apoſtles; in the ennumeration of which, the Evangel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſts place <hi>Simon Peter</hi> in the Front: And St. <hi>Matthew</hi> expreſly tells us, that he was <hi>The Firſt,</hi> that is, he was the firſt that was called to be an Apoſtle; his Age alſo, and the Gravity of his Perſon, more particularly qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifying him for a Primate of Order among the reſt of the Apoſtles, as that without which no Secreſie of Men can be managed or main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</p>
            <p>It may be here enquired, When and by whom the Apoſtles were Baptized? That they were is unqueſtionable, being themſelves appointed to Conferr it upon others. <hi>Nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorus</hi> tells us, That of all the Apoſtles, Chriſt Baptized none but <hi>Peter</hi> with his own Hands, alledging <hi>Evodius, Peter</hi>'s immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Succeſſor in the See of <hi>Antioch,</hi> for his Author; and that <hi>Peter</hi> Baptized <hi>Andrew,</hi> and the Two Sons of <hi>Zebedee,</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles: But <hi>Baronius</hi> confeſſes that this Epiſtle of <hi>Evodius</hi> is altogether unknown to the Antients.</p>
            <p>Amongſt theſe Twelve our Lord Choſe a Triumvirate to be his more intimate Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, whom he admitted, more familiarly than the reſt, unto all the more ſecret paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and tranſactions of his Life: the Three
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:44102:11"/>were <hi>Simon Peter</hi> and the Two Sons of <hi>Zebedee;</hi> theſe were with him at the Raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Jairus</hi> his. Daughter, as alſo at his Transfiguration upon the Mount, where <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> deſired our Lord that he might let them Build Three Tabernacles in memory of theſe great Tranſactions: One tells us, That in purſuance of this Petition of <hi>Peters,</hi> there were afterward Three Churches Built upon the top of this Mountain, which in after times were had in great Veneration; which poſſibly might give ſome foundation to that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port which one makes, That in his Time there were ſhewed the Ruines of theſe Three Tabernacles, which were Built according to St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s deſire.</p>
            <p>After that our Lord had entered <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in Triumph, he ſoon retired to <hi>Bethany,</hi> whence he diſpatched <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> to make Preparation for the Paſfeover; accordingly they found the Perſon whom he had deſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them, whom they followed home to his Houſe; Whether this was the Houſe of <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Evangeliſt,</hi> ſeituate near <hi>Mount Sion,</hi> or of <hi>Simon</hi> the <hi>Leper,</hi> or of <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> or of <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea,</hi> is not certain.</p>
            <p>Theſe Three alſo accompanied him to the Garden, where he laboured under his Agony; to this Garden, <hi>Euſebius</hi> tells us, That Chriſtians, even in his time, were wont to
<pb facs="tcp:44102:12"/>come Solemnly to offer up their Prayers: where alſo, another tells us, there was a fair and ſtately Church Built to the Honour of the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord being Aſcended into Heaven, and having fulfilled his Promiſe of ſending the Holy Ghoſt, the Apoſtles and Diſciples continued a while at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> being toſſed only with gentle Storms; but now a more violent Tempeſt overtook them upon the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of <hi>Stephen</hi>'s Death, which diſperſed the Diſciples, one of which, to wit, <hi>Phillip</hi> the Deacon, went to <hi>Samaria,</hi> where he Preached the Goſpel with great ſucceſs, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming the ſame with Miracles: In this place was one <hi>Simon,</hi> who by Magick and Diabolical Sorceries ſought to advance him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into a great Fame and Reputation with the People, inſomuch that they general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beheld him as the Great Power of God, for ſo the Antients tell us he uſed to Stile himſelf, giving out himſelf to be the firſt and Chiefeſt Deity, that is, That he was that which in every Nation is accounted the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Deity. The Apoſtles who were yet at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> hearing of <hi>Phillip</hi>'s ſucceſs, ſent <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> to his aſſiſtance, who when they came thither, laid their Hands upon theſe new Converts, whereupon they preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly received the Holy Ghoſt; which when <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:44102:12"/>ſaw, he offered them Money if they would conferr this Power upon him: <hi>Peter</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving his vile intentions, ſcornfully reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his impious offer, telling him, That it concerned him to Repent of ſo great and hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous a Wickedneſs.</p>
            <p>Not long after, <hi>Peter</hi> wrought a mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Cure upon one <hi>Aeneas,</hi> who had been a Cripple for a long time, and another ſoon after at <hi>Joppa</hi> upon one <hi>Tabitha;</hi> where he tarried till <hi>Cornelius</hi> called him.</p>
            <p>It was now about the end of <hi>Caligula</hi>'s Reign, when <hi>Peter</hi> after his Viſitation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing returned to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> not long after <hi>Herod-Agrippa,</hi> Grand-Child to <hi>Herod</hi> the Great, having attained the Kingdom, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to ingratiate himſelf with the People, had put St. <hi>James</hi> to Death, and finding that this gratified the vulgar, reſolved to ſend <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> the ſame way after him; in order where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, he is Apprehended and caſt in Priſon, and ſet ſtrong Watches to guard him, but the Lord by his Angel carried him out of the Priſon the Night before the intended Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo that he eſcaped: But before this, he is ſaid to have gone down to <hi>Antioch,</hi> where he Planted the Chriſtian-Faith, and there Founded a Church, and to have been the firſt Biſhop of that See. This <hi>Euſebius</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers expreſly declare.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:44102:13"/>
What became of <hi>Peter</hi> after his Deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance out of Priſon is not certainly known, probably he might have Preached in ſome parts a little farther diſtant from <hi>Judea,</hi> as we are told he did at <hi>Bizantium,</hi> and in the Countries thereabout. After this he reſolved upon a Iourney to <hi>Rome,</hi> where moſt agree, he arrived about the Second Year of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror <hi>Claudius:</hi> A Learned Author tells us, That coming to <hi>Rome</hi> he brought Proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty along with him to the City; for beſides ſeveral other extraordinary advantages which at that time happened to it, this was not the leaſt obſervable, That <hi>Camillus Scrivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianus</hi> Governour of <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> Soliciting the Army to Rebel againſt the Emperour, the <hi>Eagles,</hi> their Military <hi>Standard,</hi> remained ſo faſt in the Ground, that no power nor force was able to pluck them up; with which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſual accident, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> minds of the Souldiers were ſo amazed and ſtartled, that turning their Swords againſt the Author of the Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, continued firm and loyal in their Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, whereby a dangerous Rebellion was prevented, likely enough otherwiſe to have bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out.</p>
            <p>It is not to be doubted but that at his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival he diſpoſed himſelf among the <hi>Jews</hi> his Countrymen, who ever ſince the time of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus,</hi> dwelt in the Region beyond <hi>Tyber;</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:44102:13"/>but when afterward he began to Preach the Goſpel to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> he was forced to change his Lodging, and was taken in by one <hi>Pudens,</hi> a <hi>Senator,</hi> lately Converted to the Faith; here he cloſely plyed his Main-Office and Imployment to Eſtabliſh Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity in that place. Here, we are told, he met with <hi>Philo</hi> the Iew, who was lately come upon his Second Embaſſy to <hi>Rome</hi> in the behalf of his Country-Men at <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria,</hi> and to have contracted an intimate Friendſhip and Acquaintance with him: and now it was, that <hi>Peter</hi> being mindful of the Churches which he had lately Founded in <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, Galatia, Cappadocia, Bythinia,</hi> and <hi>Aſia</hi> the leſs, Wrote his Firſt Epiſtle to them. Next to the Planting Religion at <hi>Rome,</hi> he took care to Propagate it in the Weſtern parts, and to that end he ſent abroad Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples into ſeveral Provinces. It happened that after St. <hi>Peter</hi> had been ſeveral Years at <hi>Rome, Claudius</hi> the Emperour taking advantage of ſome Seditions and Tumults raiſed by the <hi>Jews,</hi> by a Publick Edict, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed them out of <hi>Rome,</hi> in the Number of whom (it is ſaid) St. <hi>Peter</hi> departed thence, and returned back to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and was preſent at the Great Apoſtolical Synod, where the Controverſie about Moſaical-Rites was Debated and Decided; what became of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:44102:14"/>him after this, we cannot certainly deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine; We are told by ſome that he came to the Weſtern parts, yea, that he was parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly in <hi>Brittain,</hi> where he Converted ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to the Faith; but, where ever he was, it is certain that toward the latter end of <hi>Nero</hi>'s Reign he returned to <hi>Rome,</hi> where he found the Peoples minds ſtrangely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched and hardned againſt the imbracing the Chriſtian Religion by the Subtilties and Magick-arts of <hi>Simon Magus</hi> whom he had formerly Baffled at <hi>Samaria:</hi> This <hi>Simon</hi> was Born at <hi>Gitton</hi> a Village of <hi>Samaria,</hi> Bred up in Arts of Sorcery and Divinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and by the help of the Diabolical Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers performed many ſtrange Feats and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of activity, inſomuch that the People generally looked upon him as ſome Deity come down from Heaven; but being diſcovered by St. <hi>Peter</hi> at <hi>Samaria,</hi> he left the Eaſt and fled to <hi>Rome,</hi> where by Witch-craft and Sorceries he inſinuated himſelf into the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the People, and at laſt became very acceptable to the Emperours themſelves, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that no Honour nor veneration was too great for him, eſpecially <hi>Nero,</hi> who was the Patron of <hi>Magitians,</hi> and all who main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained Secret ways of Commerce with the Infernal Powers, had a ſingular Reſpect to him: With him St. <hi>Peter</hi> thought fit in the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:44102:14"/>firſt place to encounter, and to undeceive the People by diſcovering the Impoſtures and Deluſions of the Wretched Man. Which he did thus;</p>
            <p>There was at this time at <hi>Rome</hi> an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent young Gentleman, and a Kinſman of the Emperours, lately Dead; the Fame which <hi>Peter</hi> had for raiſing of Dead perſons to Life, perſwaded his Friends to ſend for him; others alſo prevailing that <hi>Simon</hi> the <hi>Magitian</hi> might be ſent for: <hi>Simon</hi> glad of the occaſion, to magnifie himſelf before the People, propounded to <hi>Peter,</hi> That if he raiſed the Gentleman to Life, then <hi>Peter,</hi> who had provoked the Great Power of God, ſhould loſe his Life; but if <hi>Peter</hi> prevailed, he himſelf would ſubmit to the ſame Fate: <hi>Peter</hi> accepted the terms, and <hi>Simon</hi> began his Charms and Inchantments, whereat the Dead Gentleman ſeemed to move his Hand. The People that ſtood by preſently cryed out that he was alive, and that he Talked with <hi>Simon;</hi> whereupon they began to fall foul upon <hi>Peter,</hi> the Apoſtle intreated their pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, told them that all this was but a <hi>Phantaſm</hi> and appearance, that if <hi>Simon</hi> was but removed from the Bed-ſide, that all this Pageantry would ſoon evaniſh; who being accordingly removed, the Body re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained without the leaſt ſign of Motion:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:44102:15"/>
               <hi>Peter</hi> ſtanding at a good diſtance from the Bed, ſilently made his addreſs to Heaven, and then before them all Commanded the young Gentleman, in the Name of the Lord Ieſus, to Ariſe; who immediately did, ſo ſpoke, walked, and eat, and was by <hi>Peter</hi> reſtored to his Mother. The People who ſaw this, ſuddenly changed their opinion, and fell upon <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> with an intent to have Stoned him; but <hi>Peter</hi> begged his Life, and told them, It would be Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment enough for him to ſee, that in deſpite of his Malice, the Kingdom of Chriſt ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and Flouriſh.</p>
            <p>The Magician was inwardly Tormented with this Defeat, and vex'd to ſee this. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph of the Apoſtle, and therefore muſtering up all his Powers, Summoned the People and told them, That he was offended at the <hi>Galilaeans,</hi> whoſe Protector and Guardian he had been, and therefore ſet them a Day when they ſhould ſee him flee up to Heaven: at the time appointed he went up to the <hi>Mount</hi> of the <hi>Capitol,</hi> and throwing himſelf from the top of the top of the Rock, began his Flight; a ſight which the People entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with great Wonder and Veneration, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming that this muſt be the Power of God, not of Men. <hi>Peter</hi> ſtanding in the Crowd, Prayed to God that the People might be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceived,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:44102:15"/>and that the vanity of the Impoſtor might be diſcovered in ſuch a way, as he himſelf might be ſenſible of it. Immediately the Wings which he had made himſelf, began to fail him, and he fell to the Ground, miſerably bruiſed and wounded with the fall; whence being car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to a neighbouring Village he ſoon after died: But the death of this miſerable man, coming to the Emperors ears, no doubt, haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Peters</hi> ruin. The Emperor probably had been before diſpleaſed with <hi>Peter;</hi> not only upon the account of the general diſagreement, and inconformity of Religion, but becauſe he had ſo ſtrictly preſſed Temperance, and Chaſtity; and reclaimed ſo many women in <hi>Rome</hi> from a diſſolute and vicious life; whereby croſſing that Laſcivious and Wanton temper, to which that Prince was ſo immoderate a Slave; and being now by his means robbed of his dear Fovourite and Companion, he reſolved upon revenge, commanded St. <hi>Peter</hi> (as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who was at this time at <hi>Rome</hi>) to be apprehended, and caſt into his <hi>Mamer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> Priſon, where they ſpent their time in the exerciſe of Religion eſpecially in Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the priſoners, and thoſe who reſorted to them: and here we may ſuppoſe it was, that <hi>Peter</hi> wrote his ſecond Epiſtle to the diſperſed <hi>Jews;</hi> wherein he indeavours to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>m them in the belief of Chriſtianity, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:44102:16"/>to fortify them againſt thoſe pernicious Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and Practiſes, which even then began to break in upon the Chriſtian Churth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hero</hi> returning from <hi>Achaia,</hi> and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Rome</hi> with a great deal of Triumph and Pomp; reſolved now that the Apoſtle ſhould fall as a Victim to his reveng and cruelty: While the fatal ſtroak was daily expected, the Chriſtians at <hi>Rome,</hi> did, by daily, and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt prayers ſolicite <hi>Peter</hi> to make his eſcape, and to reſerve himſelf for the uſe and ſervice of the Church. This at firſt he rejected, as that would ill reflect upon his conſtancy and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage; but the prayers and tears of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, overcame him, and made him yield. At cordingly the next night, having prayed with and taken his farewell of the Bretheren, he got over the Priſon Wall, and coming to the City-Gate, he is there ſaid to have me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with our Lord, who was juſt entering the City: <hi>Peter</hi> asked him, <hi>Lord, whether art thou going?</hi> from whom he preſently received this anſwer; <hi>I am come to Rome to be Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the ſecond time.</hi> By which anſwer, <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> apprehended himſelf to be reproved, and that our Lord meant it of his death, that he was to be <hi>Crucified</hi> in his Servant; whereupon he went back to the Priſon, and delivered himſelf into the hands of his Keeper, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf moſt ready and chearful to acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſs
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:44102:16"/>in the will of God. And we are told, that in the Stone whereon our Saviour ſtood while he talked with St. <hi>Peter,</hi> he left the impreſſion of His feet; which Stone has been preſerved ever ſince, as a very Sacred Relique; and after ſeveral Tranſtations, was at length fixed in the Church of St. <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr;</hi> where it is kept and viſited with great Expreſſions of Reverence and Devotion at this day. Before his ſuffering he was ſcourg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed according to the manner of the <hi>Romans,</hi> who were wont firſt to whip thoſe Malefac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, who were adjudged to the moſt Severe and Capital puniſhments. Having ſaluted his Bretheren, and eſpecially having taken his laſt farewel of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> he was brought out of the Priſon, and lead to the top of the <hi>Vatican Mount</hi> near to <hi>Tybur,</hi> the place deſigned for his execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The heath he was adjudged to, was Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, as of all others accounted the moſt ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, ſo the moſt ſevere and terrible. But he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated the favour of the Officers, that he might not be Crucified in the ordinary way, but might ſuffer with his head downwards, and feet up to Heaven; affirming, that he was unworthy to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in the ſame poſture wherein his Lord had ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered hefore him: his body being taken down from the Croſs, is ſaid to have been Embalmed by <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellinus</hi> the <hi>Presbyter</hi> after the Iewiſh manner, &amp; was then buried in the <hi>Vatican</hi> near the <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphal
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:44102:17"/>way.</hi> Over his grave, a ſmall Church was ſoon after erected, which being deſtroyed by <hi>Heliogabalus,</hi> his body was removed to the <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meterce,</hi> in the <hi>Appian</hi> way two Miles from <hi>Rome,</hi> where it remained till the time of <hi>Pope Cornelius,</hi> who conveyed it back again to the <hi>Vatican,</hi> where it reſted ſomwhat obſcurely untill the Reign of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> who out of the mighty reverence he had for the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion, cauſed many Churches to be built at <hi>Rome;</hi> but eſpecially rebuilt and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged the <hi>Vatican</hi> to the honour of St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> in the doing whereof, himſelf is ſaid to have been the firſt that began to dig the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and to have carryed thence twelve Baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets of rubbiſh with his own hands, in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour (as it ſhould ſeem) of the twelve Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. It is ſaid, that amongſt other Reliques, here is kept that very wooden Chair wherein St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſat when he was at <hi>Rome;</hi> by the only touching whereof, many Miracles are ſaid to be performed.</p>
            <p>Having ran through the various paſſages of St. <hi>Peters</hi> life, from his Birth till his Martyrdome; it may not be amiſs in the next place to ſurvey a little his Perſon and Temper. His Body is ſaid to have been ſomwhat Slender of a middle ſize, but rather inclining to Tallneſs; his Complexion very pail and almoſt white; the Hair of his Head
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:44102:17"/>and Beard Curled and Thick, but withal Short; his Eyes black, but ſpeckt with red, which one will have to have proceeded from his frequent Weeping; his Eye-Brows thin, or none at all.</p>
            <p>Let us next look inward, and view the Iewel that was within; take him as a man, and there ſeems to have been a natural eager<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs predominant in his Temper; which as a Whetſtone, ſharpened his Soul for all bold and generous undertakings; it was this that made him expoſe his Perſon to the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent dangers; promiſe thoſe great things in behalf of his Maſter, and reſolutely draw his Sword in his quarrel againſt a whole Band of Souldiers, and wound the High-Prieſt's ſervant; and poſſibly he had attempted grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter matters, had not our Lord reſtrained, and taken him off by that ſeaſonable check that he gave him.</p>
            <p>This temper he owed in a great manner to the <hi>Genius</hi> and temper of his Country, of which <hi>Joſephus</hi> gives us this true character, that it naturally bred in men a certain fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and animoſity, whereby they were fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly carryed out upon any Action, and in all things ſhewed a mighty ſtrength and courage, both of minde and body: the <hi>Galileans</hi> being fighters from their Childhood, the men being as ſeldom taken with cowardize, as their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:44102:18"/>with want of men; and yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all this, his fervor had its Intervalls; witneſs his paſſionate crying out, when he was upon the Sea in danger of his Life, and his fearful deſerting of his Maſter in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den. But he was in danger, and paſſion pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing over his underſtanding, made him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent upon nothing but the preſent ſafety of his life; ſo dangerous it is to be left to our ſelves, and to have our natural paſſions let looſe upon us.</p>
            <p>Yet conſider him as a Diſciple and a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, and we ſhall find him eminently exampla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in the great inſtances of Religion. His humility, and lowlineſs of minde, was ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar; with what a paſſionate earneſtneſs, upon the conviction of a miracle, did he begg of our Saviour to depart from him; when our Lord by that wonderful condecenſion ſtoopt to waſh his Apoſtles feet, he could by no means be perſwaded to admit it, untill our Lord was in a manner forced to threaten him into obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; with how much candour and humility does he treat the inferior Rulers and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Church; he, upon whom Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty heaps ſo many honourable Titles, ſtiling himſelf no other than their <hi>fellow Presbyter:</hi> admirable his love to, and zeal for his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, which he thought he could never expreſs at too high a rate; for His ſake venturing upon
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:44102:18"/>the great eſtdangers, &amp; expoſing himſelf to the moſt eminent hazards of Life; telling the Iews with great plainneſs at every turn to their Faces, that they were the Murtherers and Crucifiers of the Lord of Glory; Nay, with what an Vndaunted Courage, and Heroick Greatneſs of Mind, did he tell the very <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hedrim</hi> that had Sentenced and Condemned him, that they were guilty of his murther, and that they could never be ſaved any other way, than by this very Ieſus whom they had Crucified and put to death.</p>
            <p>Conſider him alſo as an Apoſtle, and Guid of Souls, and you will find him faithful and diligent in his Office, with an infinite zeal indeavouring to inſtruct the Ignorant, reduce the Erroneous, to ſtrengthen the Weak, and confirm the Strong; we find him taking all opportunities of Preaching to people, Convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many thouſands at once: How many Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages and Travels did he undergo? with what unconquerable patience did he indure all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts and Tryals, and ſurmount all difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and oppoſitions, that he might plant and propagate the Chriſtian Faith; not thinking much to lay down his own Life to promote and further it; nor did he only do his duty him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but as one that was ſencible of the value and worth of Souls, he was care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to put others in mind of theirs; earneſty
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:44102:19"/>preſſing and perſwading the Governours and Rulers of the Church to feed the Flock of God, to take upon them the Ruling and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection of it; freely and willingly, not out of a ſiniſter end, meerly of gaining advantage to themſelves, but out of a ſincere deſign of doing good to Souls; that they would treat them mildly and gently, be themſelves exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Piety and Religion to them, as the beſt way to make their Miniſtery ſuccesful and effectual.</p>
            <p>But to conclude what we are to Remark in this great Apoſtles Life, we are in the laſt place to conſider him in his ſeveral relations; that he was married, is without all contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy, the ſacred ſtory making mention of his Wives Mother: His Wife (as ſome alledg) was the daughter of <hi>Ariſtobolus,</hi> Brother to <hi>Barnabas</hi> the Apoſtle, whom St. <hi>Jerom</hi> ſaith he left behind him, together with his Nets, when he forſook all to follow Chriſt; but <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Alexandrinus</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Peter</hi> ſeeing his wife going towards Martyrdome, exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly rejoyced that ſhe was called to ſo great an honour; and that ſhe was now returning home, encouraging, and earneſtly exhorting her, and calling her by her name, bid her be mindful of the Lord. By her, ſome ſay, he had a daughter called <hi>Petronella.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:44102:19"/>
            <head>The Life of St. <hi>PAUL.</hi>
            </head>
            <figure>
               <p>S: PAUL</p>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>ST. Paul</hi> was born at <hi>Tarſus</hi> the Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polis of <hi>Cilicia,</hi> a City infinitely Rich and Populous; and what was more to the fame
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:44102:20"/>and honour of it, an Academy furniſhed with Schools of learning, where the Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars ſo cloſely plyed their Studies, that (as <hi>Strabo</hi> tells us) they excelled in all the Arts of polite Learning and Phyloſophy; thoſe of other places, yea even of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> it ſelf, and, that even <hi>Rome</hi> was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden to it for many of its beſt Profeſſors: It was a <hi>Roman Municipium</hi> or free Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration inveſted with many priviledges by <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Caeſar,</hi> and <hi>Auguſtus;</hi> who granted to the Inhabitants of it, the honours and immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of Cityzens of <hi>Rome.</hi> In which reſpect St. <hi>Paul</hi> owned and aſſerted it as the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledg of his Birthright, that he was a <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> and thereby free from being bound or beaten.</p>
            <p>His Parents were <hi>Jews,</hi> and that of the Ancient ſtock; not entring in by the gate of <hi>Proſelytiſme,</hi> but, originally deſcended of that Nation; they belonged to the Tribe whoſe Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der was the youngeſt Son of the Old Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch <hi>Jacob,</hi> who thus propheſied of him: <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jamin ſhall ravin as a Wolfe, in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he ſhall devour the Prey, and at night devide the Spoile.</hi> This prophetical character, <hi>Tertullian,</hi> and others after him, will have to be accompliſhed in our Apoſtle; As a rave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Wolfe, in the Morning devouring the prey. That is, as a perſecuter of the Church
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:44102:20"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the firſt part of his life, deſtroying the Flock <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f God; in the Evening deviding the Spoil. That is, in his declining and reduced age, as Doctor of the Nations, feeding, and deſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uting to Chriſts Sheep.</p>
            <p>We find him deſcribed by two names in Scripture; one <hi>Hebrew,</hi> and the other <hi>Latine;</hi> probably referring both to his <hi>Jewiſh</hi> and <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Capacity and Relation: The one <hi>Saul,</hi> a name common in the Tribe of <hi>Benjamin,</hi> ever ſince the firſt being of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who was of that name, was choſen out of that Tribe; in memory whereof, they were wont to give their children that name at their Circumciſion. His other was <hi>Paul,</hi> aſſumed by him, as ſome think, at his Converſion, to denote his humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; as others, in memory of his converting <hi>Sergius Paulus</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Governor, in imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Generals and Emperors of <hi>Rome,</hi> who were wont (from the Places and Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which they conquered) to aſſume the name, as an additional honour and title to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; but this ſeems no wayes conſiſtent with the great humility of the Apoſtle. More probable therefore it is, that others think that he had a double name given him at his Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion: <hi>Saul</hi> relating to his Iewiſh Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal, and <hi>Paul</hi> relating to the Roman Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration where he was born: or, if it was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up by him afterward, probable it was done
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:44102:21"/>at his Converſion according to the cuſtom an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> manner of the <hi>Hebrews;</hi> who uſed many time<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> upon ſolemn and eminent occaſions, eſpeciall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> upon their entring upon a more Strict an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Religious courſe of Life, to change their names, and aſſume one which they had not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>In his Youth he was brought up in the Schools of <hi>Tarſus,</hi> fully inſtructed in all the Liberal Arts and Sciences, whereby he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came admirably acquainted with all Forreign Authors; together with which he was brought up to a particular Trade, and courſe of Life, according to that great Maxim and Principle of the Iewes, That <hi>he who teaches not his Son a Trade, teacheth him to be a Thief.</hi> They thought it not only fit, but a neceſſary part of Education, for the Wiſeſt and moſt Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Rabbins</hi> to be brought up to a Trade, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by if occaſion was, they might be able to maintain themſelves; hence nothing more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in their writings, than to have them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominated from their Callings; <hi>Rabbi Joſe</hi> the <hi>Tanner, Rabbi Jochanan</hi> the <hi>Shoomaker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, Rabbi Juda</hi> the <hi>Baker, &amp;c.</hi> A cuſtom, taken up by the Chriſtians, eſpecially the Monks of the primitive times; who, together with their ſtrict profeſſions, and almoſt incredible exerciſes of devotion, each took upon him a particular Trade, whereat he daily wrought; and by his
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:44102:21"/>own hand-labour maintained hemſelf: The Trade our Apoſtle was put to, was Tent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>making, whereat he wrought for ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar reaſons, even after his being called to the Apoſtolat.</p>
            <p>Having at <hi>Tarſus</hi> laid foundations of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane learning, he was by his Parents ſent to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to be perfected in the Study of the Law, and put under the Tuterage of <hi>Rabban Gamaliel;</hi> this <hi>Gamaliel</hi> was the Son of <hi>Rabban Simeon</hi> (probably ſuppoſed to be the ſame <hi>Simeon</hi> who came into the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and took <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his arms,) Preſident of the Court of the <hi>Sanhedrim;</hi> he was a Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of the Law, a Perſon of great Wisdom and Prudence; and Head at that time of one of the Families of Schools at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Chief Eminence and Authority in the Iewiſh <hi>Sanhedrim:</hi> He it was that made the wiſe and excellent Speech in the <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> in favour of the Apoſtles &amp; their Doctrine; nay, he himſelf is ſaid to have been a Chriſtian, and his ſitting in the Senate to have been connived at by the Apoſtles, that he might he the better friend to their Affairs: At the Feet of this <hi>Gamali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us he was brought up; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luding to the cuſtom of the Iewiſh Maſters, who were wont to ſit, while their Diſciples and Schollars ſtood at their feet; which honorary cuſtom was continued till the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:44102:22"/>death of this <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> and then left off.</p>
            <p>Vnder the Tuition of this great Maſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> St. <hi>Paul</hi> was educated, in the knowledg o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Law, wherein he made ſuch quick an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vaſt improvement, that he ſoon out-ſtriped a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> his fellow Diſciples; amongſt the variou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Sects at that time in the Iewiſh Church, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was eſpecially educated in the Principles an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Inſtitutions of the Phariſees, of which Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> were both his Father and his Maſter.</p>
            <p>This Sect was exceſſively proud and inſolent cenſuring whoever was not of their way, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Villains and Reprobates: All Religion an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Kindneſs with them was bound within th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> confines of their own Party; &amp; the firſt Printi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ples wherewith they inſpired their new con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts, were, That none but they were th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Godly party, and that all others were Sons of the Earth.</p>
            <p>But though this appears to have been the gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neral temper of that Party, yet doubtleſs ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were ſome among them of better and mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> honeſt Principles than the reſt; in which num<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber, we have Iuſt reaſon to reckon our Apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtle, who yet was deeply leavened with the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and fiery Genius of this ſect, not able t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> brook any oppoſite Party in Religion, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly if late and Novel; inſomuch, that when th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Iews were reſolved to do execution upon <hi>Stephen,</hi> he ſtood by and kept the cloaths o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:44102:22"/>them that did it: whether he was any further engaged in the death of this innocent and holy man, we do not find; however this was enough Loudly to proclaim his approbation and conſent.</p>
            <p>The Storm thus begun, increaſed apace, and a violent Perſecution began to ariſe, which miſerably afflicted and diſperſed the Chriſtians at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> in which our Apoſtle was a prime Miniſter and Agent, being imployed by the High Prieſt to hunt and find out theſe new upſtart Hereticks, who Preached againſt the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> (as they thought); accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly having made ſtrange havock at <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> he addreſſed himſelf to the <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> and there took out a Warrant to go down and ranſack the Synagogues at <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> whether many of the poor diſperſed Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans had fled; but God who had deſigned him for work of another Nature, ſtopt him in his Journey, drawing him back with a ſtrong hand: The particulars of which are at large ſet down in the Holy Story.</p>
            <p>Now for his Travels in <hi>Paleſtine</hi> and the adjacent Countries, as alſo his acts &amp; ſufferings in that fearful and dangerous voyage to <hi>Rome,</hi> being they are recorded particularly in the Acts of the Apoſtles; we ſhall not trouble the reader with it, but ſhall begin where it ends, and ſo meet him at <hi>Rome,</hi> whether he was ſent
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:44102:23"/>upon his appealing to <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt thing that he did after his arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val at <hi>Rome,</hi> was, to ſummon the heads of the Iewiſh Conſiſtory there, whom he acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the cauſe and manner of his coming; that though he had been guilty of no violati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Laws of their Religion; yet had he been delivered by the <hi>Jews,</hi> into the hands of the <hi>Roman</hi> Governours, who would have acquitted him once and again, as innocent of any capital Offence; but by the perverſneſs of the Iewes, he was forced (not with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to charge his own Nation) to make his <hi>Appeal</hi> to <hi>Caeſar;</hi> that being come, he had ſent for them, to let them know, That it was for his conſtant Aſſerting the Reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the hope of every true <hi>Iſraelite,</hi> that he was thus dealt with. They replyed, that they received no addice concerning him; but for his Religion, they deſired to be ſomwhat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed about it, it being every where decry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, both by <hi>Jewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles.</hi> According<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon a day appointed, he diſcourſed to them from Norning till Night, concerning the Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the Holy <hi>Jeſus;</hi> but his Diſcourſe ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not with all alike, ſome perſiſting in their infidelity, he told them plainly, That henceforth he ſhould turn his Preaching to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> who would be glad to accept, what they had ſcornfully rejected.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:44102:23"/>
It ſeems it was not long after this that he was brought to have his firſt hearing before the Emperor, where thoſe Friends which he expected ſhould ſtand by him, plainly deſerted him; but God ſtood by him, and encouraged him. Two years he dwelt at <hi>Rome,</hi> in a houſe which he had hired for his own uſe, wherein he conſtantly imployed himſelf in Preaching, and writing for the good of the Church: Convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome of all Ranks and Qualities; yea ſome belonging to the Court it ſelf, among which was <hi>Torpes,</hi> an Officer of prime note in <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes</hi> Court, and afterward a Martyr for the Faith; as alſo one of <hi>Neroes</hi> Concubines cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Pappea Chriſoſtome,</hi> alſo adds <hi>Neroes</hi> Cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearer.</p>
            <p>Amongſt others of our Apoſtles converts at <hi>Rome,</hi> was one <hi>Oneſimus,</hi> who had former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly been ſervant to <hi>Philemon,</hi> an eminent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in <hi>Coloſſe,</hi> but had run away from his Maſter, and taken things of ſome value with him: Having rambled as far as <hi>Rome,</hi> he was now Converted by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and by him returned, with recommendatory Letters to his Maſter <hi>Philemon,</hi> to beg his pardon, and to be received again into his favour.</p>
            <p>The Chriſtians at <hi>Philippi,</hi> having heard of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Impriſonment at <hi>Rome,</hi> and not knowing what ſtraits he might be reduced to, raiſed a contribution for him, and ſent it by
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:44102:24"/>the hands of <hi>Epaphroditus,</hi> who was now come to <hi>Rome,</hi> with whom, when he return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed back, <hi>Paul</hi> writ his Epiſtle to the <hi>Philip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Apoſtle being now after two years Impriſonment, perfectly reſtored to his Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, remembring that he was the Apoſtle of the Gentiles, and had therefore a larger <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs</hi> than <hi>Rome,</hi> accordingly prepared himſelf for a greater Circuit, though which way he direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Courſe, is not abſolutly certain; by ſome he is ſaid to have returned back to <hi>Greece,</hi> and the parts of <hi>Aſia;</hi> by others that he Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed both in the Eaſtern and Weſtern parts, which is not inconſiſtent with the time he had after his departure from <hi>Rome: Clemens,</hi> who was his Cotemporary in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> expreſly tells them, that, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Preacher in both the Eaſt and Weſt, he taught Righteouſneſs to the whole world, and went to the utmoſt bounds of the Weſt; probable it is, that he went into <hi>Spain,</hi> a thing which he himſelf tells us, he had formerly, once and again reſolved upon: certain it is that the ancients do generally aſſert it, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſeeming in the leaſt to doubt it. <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doret</hi> and others, tells us, that he Preached not only in <hi>Spain,</hi> but that he went alſo to other Nations, and brought the Goſpel to the Iſles of the Sea: by which they undoubtedly
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:44102:24"/>mean <hi>Brittain;</hi> and therefore elſewhere reckons the <hi>Gauls</hi> and <hi>Brittains,</hi> which the Apoſtles, and particularly the <hi>Tent</hi>-maker, perſwaded to imbrace the Law of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> nor is he the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man that has ſaid it, others alſo giving their Suffrage in this caſe.</p>
            <p>To what other Parts of the World our Apoſtle brought<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the tidings of the Goſpel, we have no certain, nor probable footſteps in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, nor any further mention of him till his return to <hi>Rome,</hi> which probably might be about the <hi>eighth</hi> or <hi>ninth</hi> year of <hi>Neroes</hi> Reign. Here he met with <hi>Peter,</hi> and were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth together thrown into Priſon; no doubt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon the Perſecution raiſed againſt the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns, under the pretence that they had fired the City: But beſides this general cauſe, we may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>robably ſuppoſe, that there were other more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>articular cauſes for his Impriſonment; ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Antients make him engaged with <hi>Peter</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> procuring the fall of that miſerable wretch <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mon Magus,</hi> and that that did cauſe the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mperors implacable fury and rage upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m: Another gives us this account of it, That having converted one of <hi>Neroes</hi> Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nes, a Woman of whom he was infinitly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd, and reduced her to a life of great ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſs and chaſtity (who formerly had been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>voted to all kind of laſciviouſneſs, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>odneſs); ſo that now ſhe altogether refu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:44102:25"/>to comply with the Emperors wanton, and impure Imbraces: The Emperor finding this, ſtormed exceedingly, calling the Apoſtle a Villain, and Impoſter, a wretched Perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and Debaucher of others; giving Orders that immediatly he ſhould be caſt into Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; but underſtanding, that for all this he ſtill perſiſted to perſwade the Lady to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue her Chaſt and Pious reſolution; he commanded him forthwith to be put to death.</p>
            <p>How long he remained in Priſon is not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly known; at laſt his Execution was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved on, that his preparitory treatment was whether ſcourged, as malefactors were won<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to be in order to their death, we cannot tell As a Roman Citizen, by the <hi>Valerian</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Parſian</hi> Law, he was exempted from it; thoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by the Law of the <hi>Twelve Tables,</hi> notoriou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> malefactors were firſt to be ſcourged, and then put to death. An Antient writer alſo tells u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> That in the Church of St. <hi>Mary,</hi> beyond t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Bridg in <hi>Rome,</hi> the Pillars are yet extan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to which both <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> were bou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> when they were ſcourged.</p>
            <p>As he was led to Execution, he is ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> have converted <hi>three</hi> of the Souldiers th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> were ſent to Conduct and Guard him, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> within few dayes after by the Emperors co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, became Martyrs for the Faith. Bei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> come to the place which was the <hi>Agnae S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viae,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:44102:25"/>three</hi> miles from <hi>Rome;</hi> after ſome ſolemn preparations, he chearfully gave his Neck to the fatal ſtroak; as a <hi>Roman,</hi> he might not be put upon the Croſs, too infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous a death for any, but the worſt of Slaves and Malefactors; and therefore was Behead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, accounted a more noble kind of death, not among the <hi>Romans</hi> only, but among other Nations, as being fitter for Perſons of bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Quality, and more ingenious Education; and from this Inſtrument of his Execution, no doubt firſt aroſe that in all Images and Pictures of the Apoſtle, he is conſtantly repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented with a Sword in his right hand.</p>
            <p>Tradition reports (which many of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers do juſtifie) that when he was Behead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, a Liquor more like Milk than Blood, flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from his Veins, and ſpurted upon the Cloaths of his Executioner, which St. <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> ſaith, became the mean of his Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, with many others, to the Faith.</p>
            <p>The ſame Father adds, that the Apoſtle ſuffered Bartyrdom about the <hi>Sixty eighth</hi> year of his Age. But ſome queſtion there is, whether he ſuffered at the ſame time with <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> Many of the Antients poſitively affirm, that both ſuffered upon the ſame day and year; but others, though allowing the ſame day, tells <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>us, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſuffered not till the year after; nay, ſome alſo go the length to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:44102:26"/>the diſtance of ſeveral years; amongſt whom is a manuſcript, of the lives and travels of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> brought amongſt many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther venerable Pieces of Antiquity out of <hi>Greece;</hi> will have <hi>Paul</hi> to have ſuffered <hi>five</hi> years after <hi>Peter,</hi> which he juſtifies by no leſs than the Authority of <hi>Juſtine Martyr</hi> and <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reneus;</hi> but what credit is to be given to this nameleſs Author, we ſee not; and therefore can lay no weight upon it, nor think it fit to be put into the Ballance, with the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of undoubted Antiquity; certainly if he ſuffered not at the very ſame time with St. <hi>Peter,</hi> it could not be long after, not above a year at moſt; the beſt of it is, which of them ſoever ſtarted firſt, they both came at laſt to the ſame end of the race, to thoſe Palms and Crowns, which are reſerved for all good men in Heaven, but moſt eminently for Martyrs of the Chriſtian Faith.</p>
            <p>He was buried in a certain place called <hi>Via Oſtienſis</hi> about the ſpace of two miles from <hi>Rome,</hi> over whoſe Grave, about the year <hi>three hundred</hi> and <hi>eighteen, Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> the <hi>Great,</hi> at the inſtance of <hi>Pope Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſter</hi> built a moſt fair and ſtately Church with in a Farm, which one <hi>Lucina,</hi> a noble and famous Chriſtian Matron of <hi>Rome,</hi> had long before Settled upon that Church; he adorned i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with an hundred of the beſt Marble Columns,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:44102:26"/>and alſo Beautifyed it with moſt exquiſite workmanſhip: The many precious Gifts of all ſorts, which this Great and Worthy Prince beſtowed upon it, are very particularly ſet down in the life of <hi>Sylveſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This being thought too narrow and little, for the honour of ſo great an Apoſtle; the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror <hi>Valentinian</hi> by a reſcript directed to <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtius</hi> Prefect of the City, cauſed it to be taken down, and began to build a more ſtately and ſpacious Church in the place of it; but <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentinian</hi> not living to ſee it finiſhed, <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius</hi> his Succeſſor did perfect it in great ſplendor, which, as Hiſtorians tell us, was fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Beautified (as appears by an antient In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription) by <hi>Placida</hi> the Empereſs, at the perſwaſion of <hi>Leo</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther additions of Wealth, Honour, and State<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs it hath ſince received, both by <hi>Popes, Emperors,</hi> and other Benefactors, were too tedious here to relate; neither is it my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince to enquire into it.</p>
            <p>As for St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Perſon, we find him thus deſcribed, He was of a little Stature, and ſomwhat Stooping, his Complection fair, his Countenance grave, his Head ſmall, his Eyes carrying a kind of ſweetneſs &amp; beauty in them, his Eye-brows a little hanging over his Noſe, long but Gracefully bending, his Beard thick, and like the Hair on his Head, mixt with Gray Hairs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:44102:27"/>
But how mean ſoever the Cabinet was, there was an unvaluable Treaſure within: for as to his Natural indowments, he ſeems to have had a clear and ſolid Iudgment, quick In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, a prompt and ready Memory; all which were abundantly improved by Art, and the advantages of a more liberal Education, which raiſed him to a mighty reputation, both for Parts and Learning.</p>
            <p>Yet all theſe were but a ſhadow to that Divine Temper of Mind that was in him, which diſcovered it ſelf through the whole courſe of his Life; he was humble to the Loweſt ſtep of condeſcention: Great was his Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance and Sobriety, ſo far from going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the bounds of regularity, that he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridged himſelf of the conveniencies of a lawful and neceſſary accommodation. His Kindneſs and Charity was truly admirable, having a compaſſionate tenderneſs for the Poor, and a quick ſenſe of the wants of others, both in their Souls and Bodies. His Zeal moſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and hot, Warning, Reproving, Intreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Perſwading by Night and by Day, by Sea and by Land; Preaching in Seaſon and out of ſeaſon. The Sum is, He was a Man in whom the Divine Life did eminently mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, and diſplay it ſelf; being alwayes careful to keep a Conſcience void of offence, both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God and Man.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:44102:27"/>
            <head>The Life of St. <hi>ANDREW.</hi>
            </head>
            <figure>
               <p>S. ANDREW</p>
            </figure>
            <p>THe Sacred Story, which has hitherto been very larg and copious, in deſcribing the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:44102:28"/>Acts of the two firſt Apoſtles, is hencefor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards very ſparing in its accounts, giveing us only now and then a few accidental re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks concerning the reſt, and ſome of them no further mentioned, than the meer recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of their names.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the Apoſtles that ſucceed, we firſt take notice of St. <hi>Andrew;</hi> he was born at <hi>Bethſaida,</hi> a City of <hi>Galilee,</hi> Son to <hi>John</hi> or <hi>Jonas,</hi> a Fiſherman of that Town, and Brother to <hi>Simon Peter;</hi> he was brought up to his Fathers Trade, whereat he wrought till our Lord called him to another kind of Fiſhing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> having lately riſen up in the Iewiſh Church; great Multitudes flock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him, to hear his diſcourſes; beſides, he had alſo a number of ſelect Diſciples, who wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more particularly upon him: In the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of which, was our Apoſtle, who was with him about <hi>Jordan;</hi> when our Lord came that way, upon his approach, the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> told them, that this was the <hi>Meſſiah;</hi> whereupon <hi>Andrew,</hi> and another Diſciple follow our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour to the place of his abode. After ſome diſcourſe with him, <hi>Andrew</hi> goes and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaints his brother <hi>Simon,</hi> and both together came to Chriſt; yet ſtayed they not long with him, but returned home, and exerciſed their Calling for more then a year, till our Lord
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:44102:28"/>paſſing through <hi>Galilee,</hi> fully ſatisfied them of his Divinity, and commanded them to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him, which they did immediatly: ſhortly after, St. <hi>Andrew,</hi> together with the reſt, was choſen to be one of thoſe that were to be Chriſt's immediate Vicegerents for planting and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting the Chriſtian Faith; little elſe is par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly recorded of him in the Sacred Story, being comprehended in the general account of the reſt of the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>Our Lord being Aſcended, and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles gone out to their work all the World o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; St. <hi>Andrew</hi> went to <hi>Scythia,</hi> where ſome of the Antients ſay he continued a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable time, going from Plate to Place, Preaching the Goſpel, and Settling Churches, meeting with a great deal of oppoſition in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places: Hence in proceſs of time, he came to <hi>Byzantium</hi> (ſince called <hi>Conſtantinople</hi>), where he inſtructed them in the knowledg of the Chriſtian Religion, and founded a Church. After this he Travelled over <hi>Thrace, Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donia,</hi> and <hi>Achaia,</hi> where for many years he Preached, and Propagated Chriſtianity; at laſt he came to <hi>Patrae,</hi> a City of <hi>Achaia,</hi> where he gave his laſt, and great Teſtimony to it, by laying down his Life for it; the manner of his Martyt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>m one deſcribeth thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aaegaas Proconſus</hi> of <hi>Achaia,</hi> coming to <hi>Patrae,</hi> and obſerving many of the people im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:44102:29"/>Chriſtianity, he endeavoured by all means to reclaim them, whereupon the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle went to him, and expoſtulated with him about the matter; but the <hi>Proconſul</hi> derided him, as the Propagator of that Religion, whoſe Author the Iews had infamouſly put to death upon the Croſs.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle from this took occaſion to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe more fully of Chriſt; but the other told him plainly, that he might perſwade them ſo that would believe him; for his part, if he would not do Sacrifice to the Gods, he would make him ſuffer upon the ſame Croſs which He ſo much extolled. Afterwards he was committed to Priſon again.</p>
            <p>The next day, he was again brought before the <hi>Proconſul,</hi> where they began to intreat one another: The <hi>Proconſul</hi> the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> that he might not fooliſhly forgo the pleaſures of this Life: The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> the <hi>Proconſul,</hi> that he might not wickedly throw away his Soul.</p>
            <p>This ſo inraged the <hi>Proconſul,</hi> that he told the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> he muſt either forſake that new Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, or reſolve to be tortured ſeverely. He replyed, that he feared not his torture, he might do his worſt; and that if he had one torture great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than another, he might heap that upon him.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Proconſul</hi> firſt commanded him to be Scourged by ſeven Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ors, ſucceſſively whipping
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:44102:29"/>his naked Body: But ſeeing his great patience, commanded him to be Crucified, but not to be faſtened to the Croſs with Nails, but Cords, that ſo his death might be more lingering and tedious.</p>
            <p>Being come within ſight of the Croſs, he heartily ſaluted it, ſaying, That he long deſired, and expected that happy hour wherein he might ſhew an honourable Teſtimony to his Glorious and Renowned Maſter. After having prayed and exhorted the people to conſtancy in that Faith, which he delivered to them, he was faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the Croſs, whereon he hung two days, Teaching, and Inſtructing the people all the time, and Exhorting them to ſuffer chearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for Chriſt and his Truth, when-ever they ſhould be called to it. And when great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities, in the mean time were uſed by ſome to the <hi>Proconſul</hi> in his behalf, he earneſtly beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of our Lord, at this time, he might Seal the Truth with his Blood. God heard his fervent prayer, and he immediatly expired on the laſt of <hi>November,</hi> though in what year, no certain account can be recovered.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:44102:30"/>
            <head>The Life of St. <hi>JAMES</hi> the Great.</head>
            <figure>
               <p>S: JACOB MAIOR</p>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>JAmes</hi> ſurnamed the <hi>Great,</hi> (either becauſe of his Age, or for ſome peculiar honours, which our Lord conferred upon him),
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:44102:30"/>was a <hi>Galilean</hi> born, the Son of <hi>Zebede</hi> a Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erman; his Mothers name was <hi>Mary,</hi> ſurnam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Salome;</hi> his Education was in the Trade of Fiſhing, which Trade his Father alſo follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; in the exerciſe of which, our Saviour found him, when he paſſed by the Sea of <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilee,</hi> where he called them to be his Diſciples; which Call, they readily obeyed, leaving their aged Father with the Servants to manage the Trade.</p>
            <p>It was not long after his firſt calling, till he was called from the ſtation of an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Diſciple, to the Apoſtolical Office; and not only ſo, but honoured with ſome peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar Acts of Favour beyond moſt of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles; being one of the three whom our Lord uſually made choice of, to admit to the more intimate Tranſactions of his Life.</p>
            <p>Thus with <hi>Peter,</hi> and his brother <hi>John,</hi> he was taken to the Miraculous raiſing of <hi>Jairus</hi> his daughter; admitted to Chriſts glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Transfiguration upon the Mount; taken along with him into the Garden, to be a ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of his bitter, and terrible Agonies.</p>
            <p>Nor was it the leaſt inſtance of that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular honour which our Lord conferred up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe Apoſtles, that at his calling of them, he gave them a new Name and Title.</p>
            <p>The Lord ſetting forward in His Iourney to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in order to his Crucifixion; and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:44102:31"/>the better to prepare the minds of his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, for his departure from them; he told them, he was to ſuffer, and yet after all, he ſhould riſe again; but they, whoſe minds were big; yet with the expectation of a Temporal Power, and Monarchy, underſtood not well the meaning of his diſcourſe: However <hi>James</hi> and his Brother ſuppoſing the Reſurrection, which he ſpoke of, would be the time when his Power and Greatneſs would commence; Prompted their Mother to put up a Petition for them; ſhe after leave, modeſtly asked for her Addreſs, beg'd of him, That when he took poſſeſſion of his Kingdom, her two Sons might have the Principal places of Honour and Dignity, next his own Perſon. Our Lord di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting his diſcourſe to the two Apoſtles, told them, they quite miſtook the nature of his Kingdom, which did not conſiſt in External Grandeur, but in Inward Life and Power; that they would do well, to conſider, whether they were able to undergo what he was to undergo. They probably not underſtanding the force of his reaſoning, anſwered, They were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to do all this; but He not taking advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of their raſh and inconſiderable Reply, told them, That as for ſuffering, they would indeed undergo it as well as he; but for any peculia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onour or dignity, he would not by any abſolute and peremptory favour of his
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:44102:31"/>own, diſpoſe of it any otherwiſe then accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thoſe Rules and Inſtructions, which he received from his Father. The reſt of the Apoſtles were offended with this Ambitious requeſt; but our Lord, to Calm their paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, diſcourſed to them at large of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Evangelick State, and its diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence from the Kingdoms of the World; with which diſcourſe the ſtorm blew over, and their exorbitant paſſions began on all hands, to be allayed and pacified.</p>
            <p>What became of St. <hi>James,</hi> after our Saviours Aſcenſion, we have no certain ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count either from the Sacred, or Eccleſiaſtick Stories: ſome affirm, that after the Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Stephen,</hi> when the Chriſtians were diſperſed, he came to the Weſtern parts of the world, even to <hi>Britain</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> and having planted Chriſtianity amongſt them, went back again to <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> but this ſeems improbable upon ſeveral accounts, and therefore its ſafeſt to confine his Miniſtry to <hi>Judea,</hi> and the parts there abouts, and to ſeek for him at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> where we are ſure to find him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod-Agrippa,</hi> Son of <hi>Ariſtobolus,</hi> being great in favour where the Emperour <hi>Claudius</hi> was ſetled, and confirmed by him in all that his Grand-Father <hi>Herod</hi> the great enjoyed, and ſeeing that this moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:44102:32"/>way to gain the affection of the Iews, was to fall heavy upon the Chriſtians; he reſolves accordingly to do it: Finding St. <hi>James</hi> Vigorous in contending for the Truth, Him he commands to be apprehended and caſt in priſon, and ſentence of death to be paſſed upon him; as he was Led forth to the place of Martyrdome, The Soldier that had guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him to the Tribunal, having been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced by that mighty courage, and conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy which St. <hi>James</hi> ſhewed at the time of his Tryal, repented of that he had done, came and fell down at the Apoſtles feet, and heartily begged pardon for what he had done againſt him. The Holy man after a little Surprize at the thing, raiſed him up and kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him: Whereupon before them all, he pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly profeſſed himſelf to be a Chriſtian, and ſo both were beheaded at one and the ſame time. Thus fell St. <hi>James,</hi> Chearfully taking that moſt bitter Cup, which formerly he told his Lord he was moſt ready to drink of.</p>
            <p>His death was not long unrevenged upon <hi>Herod,</hi> the account of it is thus: Shortly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter St. <hi>James</hi> his Martyrdom, <hi>Herod</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved to <hi>Ceſarea,</hi> while he was there, he proclaimed Solemn Sights, and Feſtival enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to be held in Honour of <hi>Caeſar:</hi> Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the morning, the ſecond day, he came
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:44102:32"/>with great State into the <hi>Theater,</hi> to make in Oration to the people, having on a moſt Sumptuous Robe, Curiouſly wrought with Silver and Gold; the Luſter of which, ſo dazled the eyes of the people, that they cryed out it was ſome <hi>Deity;</hi> and that he who ſpake, muſt be ſomthing above the ordinary Standard of Humanity. This impious ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe he received without any token of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like. But a ſudden Accident Changed the ſcene, and turned the <hi>Comick</hi> part to a black and fatal <hi>Tragedy.</hi> Looking up he eſpyed an Owle ſitting over his head, which he preſently beheld as the fatal Meſſenger of his eminent, and inevitable ruine by the juſt Iudgment of God; an incurable Melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly immediately ſeized upon his mind, as Exquiſite Torments did upon his Bowels: <hi>Behold,</hi> ſaid he, turning to thoſe about him; <hi>The Deity whom you admired,</hi> and your <hi>ſelves evidently convinced of flattery and falſehood: ſee me here by the Laws of fate condemned to die, whom juſt now you ſtyled Immortal.</hi> Being removed into the Palace, his pains ſtill increaſed upon him; and though the people mourned, and wept, faſted and prayed for his life and health, yet his accute Torments got the upper hand, and after five days put a period to his miſerable life.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:44102:33"/>
            <head>The Life of St, <hi>JOHN.</hi>
            </head>
            <figure>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. JOHN.</hi>
               </p>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>ST. John</hi> was a <hi>Galilean,</hi> the Son of <hi>Zebedee,</hi> and <hi>Salome</hi> younger bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to St. <hi>James,</hi> together with whom he
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:44102:33"/>was brought to the Trade of Fiſhing: Before his coming to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> he ſeems for ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, to have been Diſciple to <hi>John</hi> the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt, being probably that <hi>other Diſciple</hi> that was with <hi>Andrew,</hi> when they left the Baptiſt to follow our Saviour; ſo particularly does he relate all Circumſtances of the Tranſactions, though modeſtly, as in other parts of his Goſpel, concealing his own name.</p>
            <p>There is not much ſpoken concerning him in the Sacred ſtory, more than what is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded of him in Conjunction with his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>James.</hi> He was peculiarly dear to his Lord and Maſter, being <hi>the Diſciple whom Jeſus loved;</hi> witneſs his lying in our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours boſom, at the <hi>Paſchal Supper;</hi> as alſo when <hi>Peter</hi> was deſirous to know which of them our Saviour meant, when he told them, one of them ſhould betray him, and durſt not himſelf propound the queſtion, he made uſe of St. <hi>John,</hi> to ask our Lord. Indeed, when our Lord was firſt apprehended, he fled with the other Apoſtles: it not being with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out probability of reaſon, that the Ancients conceive him to have been that <hi>Young man,</hi> that followed after Chriſt having a Linen Cloath caſt about his naked body, whom when the Officers laid hold upon, he left the Linnen Cloath, and fled naked from them. But though he ſled, at preſent to avoid that ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:44102:34"/>violence that was offered to him, yet h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſoon recovered himſelf, and returned bac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to ſeek his Maſter, and waited upon him through the ſeveral paſſages of his Tryal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>till his Crucifixion. Here it was that our Saviour appointed him <hi>Guardian</hi> of his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and made her apart of his charge, and care. At the firſt news of our Lords reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, he accompanyed <hi>Peter</hi> to the Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, theſe two Apoſtles having a more mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual intimary then any of the reſt, having run many hazards together, and adhering Cloſe to one another, for the moſt part.</p>
            <p>The Antients ſay, that after the death of our Lords Mother, <hi>John</hi> went to-<hi>Aſia,</hi> where he applyed himſelf wholly to the propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating of Chriſtianity. Having planted ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral famous Churches there. Having ſpent ſome years there, he was at length accuſed to <hi>Domitian,</hi> as a Subverter of the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Empire, by whoſe command the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſul</hi> of <hi>Aſia</hi> ſent him bound to <hi>Rome,</hi> where he was put into a <hi>Cauldron</hi> of boyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Oyl: but the Divine providence brought this holy man out of this (one would thought) unavoidable deſtruction: The Cruel Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour not being ſatisfied with this, preſently orders him to be baniſhed into <hi>Patmos,</hi> a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſolate Iſland in the <hi>Archipelago,</hi> where he remained ſeveral years, inſtructing the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:44102:34"/>in the faith of Chriſt. Here it was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the latter end of <hi>Domitian's</hi> Reign, that he writ the book of the Revelations.</p>
            <p>Cruel <hi>Domitian</hi> being taken out of the way, <hi>Coccecus Nerva</hi> ſucceeded in the Empire, who being of a milder tempee, reſcinded the odious acts of his predeceſſor, recalling the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed; whereupon St. <hi>John</hi> left <hi>Patmos,</hi> and returned to <hi>Aſia,</hi> fixing his reſidence at <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> where it is ſaid he wrote his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel.</p>
            <p>He lived till the time of <hi>Trajan:</hi> about the beginning of whoſe Reign, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted this life, about the Ninety eighth, or Ninty nineth year of his life, as is generally thought. But others think that he dyed a Martyr, upon no other ground, then of that our Saviour told him and his brother: That they ſhould drink of the cup, and be Baptized with the Baptiſm wherewith he was Baptized, which was indeed Literally verified of his brother <hi>James.</hi> Yet for him though (as. one obſerves) he was not put to death, yet may he be truly ſtylled a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, his being put in a Veſſel of Boiling Oil, his many years baniſhment, and other ſufferings in the cauſe of Chriſt, Iuſtly Challenging the Title, it being not want of good will either in him, or his enemies; but the divine providence Immediately over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruling
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:44102:35"/>the powers of nature, that kept the Malice of his enemies from its full execution.</p>
            <p>Others deny that he dyed at all, but is ſtill alive; the foundation of which error, was foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon what paſſed between our Lord and <hi>Peter,</hi> concerning this Apoſtle: for Chriſt having told <hi>Peter,</hi> what was to be his own fate, <hi>Peter</hi> enquires what would become of St. <hi>John.</hi> To whom the Lord anſwered, <hi>If I will that he tarry till I come, what is that to thee;</hi> which was miſ-underſtood by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles; though St. <hi>John</hi> himſelf, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords that paſſage, inſerts a cauſion, <hi>That Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus did ſay he ſhould not die.</hi> From the ſame Original alſo ſprang this report, That he on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lay ſleeping in his grave at <hi>Epheſus;</hi> which report, was for a long time current.</p>
            <p>He ſeems to have always led a ſingle life; and ſo the Antients tells us, that all the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles were marryed, except St. <hi>John</hi> and St. <hi>Paul:</hi> He was poliſhed by no arts of learning, but his want of it was made up abundantly in his Excellent Temper of mind, and the furniture of divine gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which he was adorned withall: His Humility was admirable, ſtudiouſly concealing his own Worth and Honour.</p>
            <p>He ſhewed a mighty care to the ſouls of men, unwearied by ſpending himſelf in the ſervice of the Goſpel; Travelling from
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:44102:35"/>Eaſt to Weſt, to leaven the world with the principles of that Holy Religion, which he was ſent to propagate. He was infinitely Vigilant againſt Hereticks, Countermining there Artifices, Antidoting againſt the poyſon of their errors, and ſhuning all communion and converſation with their perſons.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:44102:36"/>
            <head>The Life of <hi>St. PHILIP.</hi>
            </head>
            <figure>
               <p>S. PHILIP</p>
            </figure>
            <p>OF all parts of <hi>Paleſtine, Galilee</hi> ſeems to to have paſſed under the greateſt character of Ignominy &amp; Reproach; therefore called <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilee
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:44102:36"/>of the Gentiles:</hi> both <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile</hi> conſpiring in this, that they thought they could not fix a greater title of reproach upon our Saviour and His followers, than that of <hi>Gali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lean.</hi> But to confute this, our Lord choſe hence, thoſe excellent Perſons, whom he made the great inſtruments to Convert the World; ſome of which we have already given account of, and more are yet behind.</p>
            <p>Of this number was <hi>Philip,</hi> born at <hi>Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaida,</hi> a Town near the Sea of <hi>Tiberias:</hi> Of his Parents, and way of Life, the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Goſpel takes no notice; though pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably he was a Fiſherman, the common Trade of that place: He had the honour to be the firſt called to be Chriſts Diſciple; which came thus to paſs. Our Lord, after His return from the Wilderneſs, having met with <hi>Andrew,</hi> and his brother <hi>Peter,</hi> after ſome ſhort diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe parted from them; and the next day paſſing through <hi>Galilee,</hi> he found <hi>Philip,</hi> whom he commanded preſently <hi>to follow him,</hi> which he accordingly did.</p>
            <p>No ſooner had Religion taken poſſeſſion of his mind, then away he goes, and Finds <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaniel,</hi> acquaints him with the tydings of the new-found <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> and conducts him to Him: After his call to the Apoſtleſhip, there is not much recorded of him in the Holy Story. It was to him that the Lord propounded the queſtion,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:44102:37"/>what they ſhould get in the Wilderneſs, as would feed ſo vaſt a multitude; To which he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, That ſo much was not eaſily to be had. It was to him, that the <hi>Gentile Proſylites</hi> that came up to the Paſſover, addreſſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, when they deſired to ſee our Saviour. It was with him that our Lord diſcourſed concerning himſelf, a little before the laſt paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal Supper. The Lord Ieſus had been forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying their minds with fit conſiderations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his departure from them: He told them, That <hi>no man could come to the Father, but by Him. Philip</hi> not duely underſtanding the force of our Saviours reaſonings, begged of him, that he would ſhew them the Father. Our Lord gently reproved his ignorance, that after ſo long attendance upon his inſtructions, he ſhould not know that he was the Image of his Father; the expreſs character of his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Wisdom, Power and Goodneſs appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in him; that he ſaid, and did nothing, but by his Fathers appointment, which if they did not believe, his Miracles were a ſufficient evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; that therefore ſuch demands were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary, and impertinent, and that it argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed great weakneſs after more than three years education under his diſcipline and inſtruction, to be ſo unskilful in thoſe matters.</p>
            <p>In the diſtribution of the ſeveral Regions of the World made by the Apoſtles; ſome think
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:44102:37"/>that the <hi>upper Aſia</hi> was the Province which was aſſigned to <hi>Philip,</hi> where he applyed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with an indefatigable diligence and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, to recover men out of the ſnare of the Devil, to the imbraceing and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of the Truth, by conſtancy of his Preaching, and Efficacy of his Miracles, he gained numerous Converts, whom he Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized to the Chriſtian Faith; at once Curing both Souls and Bodies: their Souls of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and Idolatry, their Bodies of Infirmities and Diſtempers; healing Diſeaſes, diſpoſſeſſing <hi>Daemons;</hi> ſettling Churches, and appointing them Paſtors and Teachers.</p>
            <p>Having for many years ſuccesfully manag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Apoſtolical Office in thoſe parts, he came, towards the latter part of his life, to <hi>Hierapolis</hi> in <hi>Phrygia,</hi> a Rich and Populous, but moſt Idolatrous Place: Amongſt the many Vain and Trifleing Deities, to whom they payed Religious Worſhip, was a <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent</hi> or <hi>Dragon,</hi> which they Worſhipped with great and ſolemn Veneration: the Apoſtle was grieved to ſee them ſo groſely inſlaved to Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror; and therefore continually ſolicited Heaven, till by Prayer he had protured the death (at leaſt vaniſhing) of this Famed Creature: Which done, he told them how unbecoming it was, to give Divine honours to ſuch odious creatures; and thence took occaſion to diſcourſe at large of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:44102:38"/>Chriſtianity. The ſucceſs was, That the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were aſhamed of their groſs Idolatry; and many broke looſe from their Chains of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, and ran over to Chriſtianity; whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the great enemy of Mankind, betook him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to his old Methods, Cruelty and Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution; the Magiſtrates of the City ſeized the Apoſtle, and having put him into Priſon, cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him to be ſeverely Scourged. This prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratory Cruelty paſſed, he was led to Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and being bound, was hanged up by the Neck againſt a Pillar, though others tell us that he was Crucified; the Apoſtle being dead, his body was taken down by St. <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholomew</hi> his fellow Sufferer, and his own Siſter, who is ſaid to have been the conſtant companion of his travels, and decently buried; after which, having Confirmed the people in the Faith of Chriſt, they departed from thence.</p>
            <p>It is generally affirmed, that St. <hi>Philip</hi> was Married, and that he had Daughters, whom he diſpoſed in Marriage; but though this be granted, as it is not improbable; yet the not carefully diſtinguiſhing between <hi>Philip</hi> the Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, &amp; <hi>Philip</hi> the Apoſtle; has bred ſome confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on among the Antients in this matter; inſomuch that ſome have concluded them to be one and the ſame perſon; but with how little reaſon, will appear to any that ſhall conſider, that <hi>Philip,</hi> who was choſen to be one of the Seaven
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:44102:38"/>Deacons, could not be one of the Apoſtolical Colledg; the Apoſtles declaring upon that oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion that they had affairs of a higher na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to attend upon: So then upon the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution that aroſe, upon St. <hi>Stephens</hi> death, the Church was diſperſed; <hi>they were all ſcattered abroad throughout the Regions of Judea and Samaria,</hi> (and <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>Deacon,</hi> among the reſt who went down to the City of <hi>Samaria</hi>) <hi>except the Apoſtles</hi> who tarried be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> &amp; when <hi>Philip</hi> had Convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Baptiſed a conſiderable number in that place, he was forced to ſend for two of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that ſo by their hands they might receive the Holy Ghoſt, which had been wholly needleſs, had he himſelf been of the twelve Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Philip</hi> was one of the Apoſtles, who left no ſacred writings behind him; the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part of the Apoſtles, having little leaſure to write Books, being imployed in the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry more immediately uſeful, and ſubſervient to the happineſs of Mankind.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:44102:39"/>
            <head>The Life of St. <hi>BARTHOLOMEW</hi>
            </head>
            <figure>
               <p>
                  <hi>S:</hi> BARTHOLOME</p>
            </figure>
            <p>IT is not queſtioned at all, but that S. <hi>Bartholomew</hi> was an Apoſtle; but the Holy Story, taking no further notice of him,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:44102:39"/>then the bare mention of his name gave oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to many both Antient and Modern, not without occaſion to Suppoſe, that he lies conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under ſome other name, and that this can be no other than <hi>Nathaniel,</hi> one of the firſt Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples that came to Chriſt, accordingly we may obſerve that as ſome of the Evangeliſts, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver mention <hi>Bartholomew</hi> in the number of the Apoſtles, ſo others take no notice of <hi>Nathaniel,</hi> propably. But that which renders the thing moſt ſpecious, and probable is that we find <hi>Nathaniel,</hi> particularly reckoned up with the other Apoſtles, to whom our Lord appeared at the Sea of <hi>Tiberias.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This difficulty being cleared, we proceed to a more particular account of him: By ſome he is thought to have been a <hi>Syrian</hi> of a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Extract, and to have derived his extract from the <hi>Ptolemes</hi> of <hi>Aegypt.</hi> But it is plain that he as the reſt of the Apoſtles was a <hi>Galilean;</hi> and of <hi>Nathaniel</hi> we know it is particularly ſaid, that he was of <hi>Cana</hi> in <hi>Galilee;</hi> the Scripture takes no notice of his Trade or way of life, though ſome Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances might ſeem to intimate that he was a fuſherman. At his firſt coming to Chriſt he was conducted by Philip, who told him that they had found the long-looked-for <hi>Meſſiah;</hi> and when he obſerved that the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> could not be born at Nazareth, <hi>Philip</hi> bids him
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:44102:40"/>come, and ſatisfie himſelf; at his firſt appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, the Lord entertains him with the Character of a man of true ſimplicity, and Integrity: Surprized he was at our Lords Salutation, wondring how he could know him ſo well at firſt ſight, whoſe face he had never ſeen before; But he was anſwered, that he had ſeen him, while he was under the Fig Tree, before <hi>Philip</hi> called him. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced with this inſtance of our Lords Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, he preſently made his confeſſions, that now he was ſure that <hi>Jeſus</hi> was the promiſed <hi>Meſſiah</hi> the Son of God, whom he had appointed to be the King, and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of his Church: Our Saviour told him, that if upon theſe inducements he could be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him to be the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> he ſhould have far greater arguments to confirm his faith; yea, that err long he ſhould behold the Heavens opened to receive him thither, and the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels Viſibly appearing to wait; and attend upon him.</p>
            <p>Concerning our Apoſtles Travels up and down the world, to propagate the Chriſtian Faith, we ſhall preſent the reader with a brief account of them from Antiquity; that he went as far as <hi>India</hi> is owned by all, which muſt be meant, only of that part of <hi>India</hi> lying next to <hi>Aſia;</hi> yet others ſay it was the <hi>India,</hi> bordering upon <hi>Aethiopia,</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:44102:40"/>and alſo tell us that here he left St. <hi>Mathews</hi> Goſpel: The particular relation of which a famous Author giveth thus; that when <hi>Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenus</hi> a man famous for his skill in Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy, and eſpecially in the inſtitutions of the ſtoicks, but much more for his hearty af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to Chriſtianity, in a devout, and Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous imitation of the Apoſtles, was inflamed with a deſire to propagate the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, unto the Eaſtern Countrys: He came as far as <hi>India</hi> it ſelf, here among ſome, that yet retained the knowledge of Chriſt, he found St. <hi>Mathews</hi> Goſpel written in He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; left here as the Tradition was by St. <hi>Bartholomew,</hi> one of the Twelve A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, when he Preached the Goſpel to theſe Nations.</p>
            <p>After his Labours in theſe parts of the world, he returned to the more Weſtern, and Northern parts of <hi>Aſia.</hi> At <hi>Herapolis</hi> in <hi>Phrygia</hi> we find him in company with <hi>Philip,</hi> inſtructing that place in the principles of Chriſtianity, and convinceing them of the folly of their blind Idolators: Here, by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, he was at the ſame time with <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip,</hi> deſigned for Martyrdom, in order there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, he was faſtned upon the Croſs, with intent to diſpatch him; but upon a ſudden Conviction, that the Divine Iuſtice would Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge their death, he was taken down and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:44102:41"/>diſmiſſed. Hence it is probable that he went to <hi>Lyconia.</hi> His laſt remove was to <hi>Albanople,</hi> in <hi>Armenia</hi> the great, a place miſerably o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-grown with Idolatry, from which, while he ſought to reclaim the people, he was by the Governour of the place, commanded to be Crucified, which he Chearfully under-went, comforting and confirming the convert-Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles to the laſt minute of his life; ſome add, that he was Crucified with his head down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, others that he was flead, and his skin firſt taken off, which might conſiſt well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough with his Crucifixion; Exeoriation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a puniſhment in uſe, not only in <hi>Egypt,</hi> but among the <hi>Perſians;</hi> and from whom they might have borrowed this piece of Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Cruelty.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:44102:41"/>
            <head>The Life of St. <hi>Mathew,</hi>
            </head>
            <figure>
               <p>St. Matthew.</p>
            </figure>
            <p>St. <hi>Mathew</hi> called alſo <hi>Levi,</hi> was, though a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man officer, an <hi>Hebrew</hi> of the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> and probably a Galican; he was the Son of <hi>Alpheus,</hi>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:44102:42"/>and <hi>Mary</hi> Siſter or Kinswoman to the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Virgin. His way of life was that of a publican, or toll gatherer to the Romans, an office of bad report, among the <hi>Jews;</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, among the Romans, it was a place of power and credit, and Honourable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>tati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not ordinarily conferred upon any b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Knights. The <hi>Jews</hi> thought this Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice odious, upon theſe two accounts firſt that the perſons, that managed it, were uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally covetous, and great exacters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which doubtleſs <hi>Zacheus</hi> was ſenſible of, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his converſion he offered fourfold Reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions to any man, from whom he had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken any thing by fraud, and evil arts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and upon this account they became unfamous, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven among the Gentiles themſelves. The other thing that made the <hi>Jewes</hi> deteſt them, was that this Tribute was not only a grievance to their purſes, but an affront to the liberty, and freedom of their nations, for they looked upon themſelves, as a free-born people in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted in this priviledge immediately by God himſelf, and therefore looked upon this as a daily, and ſtanding inſtance of their ſlavery.</p>
            <p>Hereby Publicans, became Vniverſally to be abhorred by the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Nation, that it was accounted unlawful for them to ſhew ſuch men any Courteſie or Common kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Of this Trade and Office was our
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:44102:42"/>St. <hi>Mathew,</hi> and it ſeems more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to have conſiſted in gathering the Cuſtoms of Commodities, that came by the Sea of Galilee; and the Tribute the Paſſengers were to pay, that went by water, a thing frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mentioned in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> writings. For this purpoſe they kept their Office or Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome-houſe by the Sea ſide, that they might always be near at hand; and here it was, that St. <hi>Mathew</hi> had his Tol-booth, where he ſate at the receipt of Cuſtom; Chriſt having lately cured a famous <hi>Paralitick,</hi> retired out of <hi>Capernaum</hi> to walk by the Sea-ſide; where he taught the people that flocked after him. Here he eſpyed <hi>Mathew</hi> ſitting in his Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome-Office, whom he called to come, and follow him; the man was rich, had a weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and gainful Trade, but he overlooked all theſe conſiderations, left all his intereſts, and Relations to become our Lords Diſciple; and to ſhew that he was not diſcontented with his choice, nor apprehended himſelf a looſer by this bargain, he entertained our Lord, and his Diſciples at a great dinner in his houſe, whether he invited his friends, eſpecially thoſe of his own profeſſion.</p>
            <p>After his Election to the Apoſtolate, he continued with the reſt, tell our Lord's Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and then for the firſt eight years at leaſt preached up and down <hi>Judea.</hi> After
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:44102:43"/>which, being to betake himſelf to the Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Gentile World, he was intreated by the Convert Iews to commit to Writing the Hiſtory of our Lords Life and Actions, and to leave it among them, as a ſtanding Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of that he had Preached to them, which he did accordingly, and ſo compoſed his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel; little certainty can be had, what Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels he underwent for the advancement of the Chriſtian Faith. Some tell us that he went into <hi>Parthea,</hi> &amp; having ſucceſsfully plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Chriſtianity in thoſe Parts, thence travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into <hi>Aethiopia,</hi> where by Preaching, and Miracles, he mightily Triumphed over Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and Idolatry.</p>
            <p>As to the manner of his death, it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated by ſome, that he went into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of the <hi>Canibals,</hi> where Chriſt appeared to him in the form of a beautiful Youth, and gave him a Wand, which he pitching in the ground, immediately it grew up into a Tree, that he alſo miraculouſly Converted the Prince of the Country, and after all, dyed in peace, and was moſt ſumptuouſly buryed: But others of the Antients, with as much probility, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm that he ſuffered Martyrdom at a City in <hi>Aethiopia;</hi> but that kind of death is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether uncertain.</p>
            <p>He was a great inſtance of the power of Religion; how much a man may be b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:44102:43"/>off to a better temper, if we reflect upon his circumſtances, while yet a ſtranger to Chriſt we ſhall find the world had very great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages upon him, and yet notwithſtanding, no ſooner did Chriſt call, but without the leaſt ſcruple or diſſatisfaction, not only renounced his gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful incomes, but ran an immediate hazard of the diſpleaſure of his Maſters the <hi>Romans,</hi> that had imployed him for quitting their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and leaving his accounſs intangled and confured behind him.</p>
            <p>The laſt thing remarkable in the Life of this Apoſtle, is, his Goſpel Written at the intreaty of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> converts, and as ſome ſay, at the command of the Apoſtles while he was yet in <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> eight years after the death of Chriſt, which St. <hi>Bartholomew</hi> took along with him into <hi>India,</hi> and left there: He wrot it in <hi>Hebrew,</hi> as primarily deſigned it for the uſe of his Country-men; it was without doubt, ſoon after tranſlated into <hi>Greek,</hi> as ſome think by St. <hi>John;</hi> others attribute the tranſlation of it to St. <hi>James the leſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After the <hi>Greek</hi> tranſlation was enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Copy was chiefly owned, and uſed by the <hi>Nazarens,</hi> a middle Sect of men between Iewes and Chriſtians; what the Chriſtians, they believed in Chriſt, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced his Religion; what the Iews, they adhered to the Rites and Ceremonies of the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:44102:44"/>
               <hi>Moſaick</hi> Law, and hence this Goſpel came to be ſtyled <hi>the Goſpel of the Hebrews, and the Goſpel of the Nazarenes;</hi> by them it was by degrees interpolated ſeveral paſſages of the Evangelical Hiſtory, which they heard from the Apoſtles; or thoſe who had familiarly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed with them, being inſerted; which the Antients Fathers frequently refer to in their writings: This Hebrew Copy was found in the Treaſury of the <hi>Jewes</hi> at <hi>Tiberias,</hi> by <hi>Joſeph</hi> a Iew, and after his Converſion a man of great Honour &amp; Eſteem; in the days of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,</hi> one of the Antients aſſures us that there was another kept in the Library of <hi>Caeſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea,</hi> in his time; and another by the <hi>Nazarenes</hi> at <hi>Berea,</hi> from whom he had the liberty to Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe it, and which he afterward Tranſlated both into Greek and Latine: A Copy alſo of this Goſpel was dug up and found in the Grave of <hi>Barnabas</hi> in <hi>Cyprus,</hi> Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed with his own hand, but theſe Copies are long ſince periſhed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:44102:44"/>
            <head>The Life of St. <hi>THOMAS.</hi>
            </head>
            <figure>
               <p>S: THOMAS</p>
            </figure>
            <p>THe <hi>Jews</hi> uſed commonly (when Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into forreign Countries, or familiarly converſing with the <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Romans</hi>) to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:44102:45"/>aſſume to themſelves a <hi>Greek</hi> or a <hi>Latine</hi> name, of affinity, and ſometimes of the very ſame ſignification with that of their own Country. Thus our St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> according to the <hi>Syriacks</hi> importance of his name, was called <hi>Didimus,</hi> which is the ſame with his other name, expreſſed in different Languages. The Hiſtory of the Goſpel takes no particular notice, either of his Country or Kindred; that he was a Iew is certain, and in all proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility a <hi>Galileean;</hi> he was born (as ſome ſaith) of very mean Parents, brought up to the Trade of Fiſhing: He was afterwards, together with the reſt, called to the Apoſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, where, not long after he gave an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent inſtance of his hearty willingneſs to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo the ſaddeſt Fate that might attend them, for when the reſt of the Apoſtles, diſſwaded our Saviour from going to <hi>Judea,</hi> leſt the Iewes ſhould ſtone Him, as but a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they had attempted it: St. <hi>Thomas</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires them not to hinder Chriſts Iourney thither, though it might coſt them their Lives, proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly concluding, that inſtead of raiſing <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> from the dead, they themſelves ſhould be ſent with him to their own Graves; ſo that he made up, in pious a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fections, what he ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to want in the quickneſs of his underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, not readily apprchending ſome of our Lords diſcourſes, nor overforward to believe more
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:44102:45"/>than himſelf had ſeen; when Chriſt, a little before his fatal ſufferings, told his Diſciples, that he was going to prepare for them that they might follow, and that they knew the place whether he was a going, and the way thither. Our Apoſtle Roundly replyed, that they knew it not: To which, our Lord gives this ſatisfactory anſwer, That he was the true Living Way.</p>
            <p>Our Lord being dead, the Apoſtles were exceedingly diſtracted, between hope and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair concerning his reſurrection, which enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged him the ſooner to haſten his appearance; wherefore, the very day in which he aroſe, he came into the houſe, in which they were, while for fear of the <hi>Jews</hi> the Dores were faſt ſhut about them: At this Meeting St. <hi>Thomas</hi> was abſent, having probably never recovered their company ſince their laſt diſperſion in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, where every owns Fears prompted him to Conſult his own ſafety. At his return, they told him, That the Lord had appeared to them, but he obſtinately refuſed to believe that it was he, except he might ſee the very prints of the Nails and feel, the Wounds in his Hands and Sides: But his compaſſionate maſter would not take advantage of the man's re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractory unbelief; but upon that Day ſeven night came to them, as they were ſolemnly met at their Devotions, and calling <hi>Thomas,</hi>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:44102:46"/>hade him look upon his Hands, &amp; put his Fingers into the prints of the Nails, and thruſt his Hand into the hole of his Side, and thereby ſatisfy his Faith. The Man was quickly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of his Error, confeſſing, That he now acknowledged him to be his very Lord and Maſter.</p>
            <p>Our Lord being Aſcended, and having emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently given Gifts, and miraeulous Powers to the Apoſtles. St. <hi>Thomas</hi> moved thereto by divine Intimation, is ſaid to have diſpat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched <hi>Thaddaeus,</hi> one of the <hi>Seventy</hi> Diſciples to <hi>Abgaras,</hi> King of <hi>Edeſſa,</hi> whom he firſt Cured of an inveterate Diſtemper, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Converted him and his Subjects to the Faith. The Apoſtolical Aſſigned to St. <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas,</hi> was <hi>Parthia,</hi> after which, ſome inform us, he preached the Goſpel to the <hi>Medes, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians, Carmans, Horcany, Bactrians,</hi> and the Neighbour Nations. One of the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents ſaith, That in <hi>Perſia</hi> he met with the Wiſe Men, who came that long Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eney from the Eaſt, to bring Preſents to our New-Born Saviour, whom he Baptized, and took along with him, as his Companions and Aſſiſtants in propagation of the Goſpel; Hence he Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in, and paſſed through <hi>Aethiopia,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward came to <hi>India,</hi> where we are told he was affraid to have ventured himſelf, until he was encouraged by a Viſion, that aſſured
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:44102:46"/>him of the divine Preſence to aſſiſt him. He Travelled a great way in theſe Eaſtern Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as far as the Country of the <hi>Brach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> Preaching every where, where by mild and Gentle methods, he brought over the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from their groſſeſt Superſtition and Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Portugals</hi> tell us, that St. <hi>Thomas</hi> came firſt to <hi>Socotara,</hi> an Iſland in the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabian</hi> Sea; thence to <hi>Canyanor,</hi> where hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing converted many, he travelled farther into the Eaſt; and having ſucceſsfully preached the Goſpel, returned back to <hi>Carmandal,</hi> where he began to Erect a Place for Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, till prohibited by the Prieſt and the Prince of the Country: But upon conviction of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Miracles, the work went on, and the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gamo</hi> or King himſelf imbraced the Chriſtian Faith. The <hi>Brachmans,</hi> who plainly perceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that this would certainly ſpoil their Trade, and in time extirpate the Religion of their Country; thought it high time to put a ſtop to its growing, and reſolved in Council, that ſome way or other the Apoſtle muſt be put to death. There was a Tomb not far from the City, whether the Apoſtle was wont to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire to his Solitudes and private Devotions. Hither the <hi>Brachmans</hi> and their followers, perſued him, and while he was intent at prayer, they firſt loaded him with Darts and
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:44102:47"/>Stones, till one of them coming nearer, ran him through with a <hi>Launce.</hi> His Body was taken up by his Diſciples, and buried in the Church, which he had lately built.</p>
            <p>While one of the Vice-Royes of <hi>Portugal</hi> reſided in thoſe parts, there were brought to him certain Braſs Tables, whoſe Inſcriptions none could read, till at laſt, by the help of a Iew, they were found to contain nothing but a donation made to St. <hi>Thomas</hi> of a piece of Ground for the building of a Church. They tell us alſo of a famous Croſs found in St. <hi>Thomas</hi> his Chappel, wherein was an untelligible Character, which learned <hi>Dramin</hi> rendred to this effect: That <hi>Thomas</hi> a Divine perſon was ſent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe Countries by the Son of God, in the days of King <hi>Sagamo,</hi> to inſtruct them in the knowledg of the true God, that he built a Church, and performed admirable Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, but at laſt, while upon his Knees at prayer, was thruſt through with a Spear, and that the Croſs ſtained with his blood was left as a memoral of theſe matters.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:44102:47"/>
            <head>The Life of St. <hi>JAMES</hi> the Leſs.</head>
            <figure>
               <p>St. JACOB MINOR.</p>
            </figure>
            <p>HE was the Son (as we may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably conjecture) of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward the Husband of the Bleſſed
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:44102:48"/>Virgin, by his firſt Wife. Hence re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted our Lords Brother, in the ſame ſenſe that he was reputed the Son of <hi>Joſeph.</hi> One thing there is that ſeem to lye againſt this, that he is called the Son of <hi>Alpheus,</hi> but this may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably mean no more than either that <hi>Joſeph</hi> was ſo called by another name, or it may relate to his being a Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, of ſome particular Sect among the Iews, called <hi>Alpheans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of the place of his birth, the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Story makes no mention. The Iews frequently ſtyle him a man of the Town of <hi>Sechania</hi> though, where that place was, we are not able to conjecture; what was his particular way and courſe of Life, before his being called to the Diſcipleſhip and Apoſtolate, we find no intimations of in the Hiſtory of the Goſpel, nor any diſtinct account concerning him, during our Saviours Life. After the reſurrection, he was honoured with a particular appearance of our Lord to him, which, though ſilently paſſed over by the Evangeliſts,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:44102:48"/>is recorded by <hi>Paul.</hi> One of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients gives us a fuller account of it, which is, that <hi>St. James</hi> had ſolemnly ſworn, That from the time that he had drank of the Cup at the Inſtitution of the Supper, he would eat Bread no more, till he ſaw the Lord riſen from the dead. Our Lord therefore being returned from the Grave, came and appeared to him, commanded Bread to be ſet before him, which he took, bleſſed, and beake, and gave to <hi>St James,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Eat thy Bread my Brother, for the Son of Man is truly riſen from among them that Sleep.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His reſidence was for the moſt part at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> being the Biſhop and Paſtor of it. To him we find <hi>St. Paul</hi> make his addreſs, after his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion. To him <hi>St. Peter</hi> ſent the newes of his miraculous deliverance out of Priſon. But he was princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally active in the <hi>Synod</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in the great controverſie about the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaick</hi> Rites.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:44102:49"/>
He diſcharged his Office with all poſſible care and induſtry, omitting no part of a diligent and faithful Guide of Souls; ſtrengthening the Weak, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming the Ignorant, reducing the Erroneaus, reproving the Obſtinate; and by the conſtancy of his Preaching, conquering the ſtubbornneſs of that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractory and perverſe Generation that he had to deal with; many of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler and Better Sort being brought over to a complyance with the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Faith, which awakened the ſpite and malice of his enemies to conſpire his ruin. Vexed they were that <hi>St. Paul</hi> (by appealing to <hi>Caeſar</hi>) had eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped their hands, and therefore now they turn their revenge upon <hi>St. James,</hi> which they not being able to affect un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Feſtus</hi>'s Government, they more effectually attempted under the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curatorſhip of <hi>Albinus</hi> his Succeſſor; reſolving to diſpatch him before the new Government could arrive: To this end a Council is haſtily ſummon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the Apoſtle with others Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigned
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:44102:49"/>and Condemned as Violators of the Law; but that the thing might be carried in a more platiſible and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular way, they ſet the Scrives and Phariſees at work to inſnare him; who coming to him, began with flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Inſinuations to ſet upon him: They tell him, that they all had a mighty Confidence in him, and that the whole Nation gave him the Teſtimony of a Iuſt Man; that therefore they deſired he would Correct the Error, and falſe Opinion, which the People had of <hi>JESUS,</hi> whom they looked upon as the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> and would take their Opportunity of their Vniverſal Confluence to the paſchal Solemnity, to ſet them right in their notions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout theſe things, and would to that end go up with them to the top of the Temple, where he muſt be ſeen and heard by all. Being advantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly placed upon a Pinacle or Wing of the Temple, they made this Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs to him. <hi>Tell us, O</hi> Iuſtus, <hi>whom we have all the reaſon in the world
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:44102:50"/>to believe, that ſeeing the People are thus generally led away with the Doctrine of <hi>JESUS</hi> that was Crucified; tell us what is this Inſtitution of the Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied <hi>JESUS?</hi>
               </hi> To which the Apoſtle anſwered with an audable voice, <hi>Why do ye inquire concerning <hi>JESUS</hi> the Son of Man? He ſits in Heaven on the right Hand of the Majeſty on high, and will come again in the Clouds of Heaven.</hi> The People be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, hearing it, glorifi'd the Bleſſed <hi>Jeſus.</hi> The <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving now, that they had overſhot themſelves, and that inſtead of reclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they confirmed the People in their ſuppoſed Error, thought that there was no way ſeft, but preſently to diſpatch him, that by his ſad fate, others might be warned not to believe him: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſuddenly crying out, that <hi>Juſtus</hi> himſelf was ſeduced, and become an Impoſtor; they threw him down from the place where he ſtood, though brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, he was not killed by the fall, but recovered ſo much ſtrength, as to get
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:44102:50"/>upon his knees, and pray to Heaven for them; vexed that they had not done his work, they fell freſh upon the poor remainders of his Life; and while he was yet at prayer, and One ſtepping in, and intreating them to ſpare him; a Iuſt and Religious man, and who was then praying for them; they began to load him with a ſhower of ſtones, till one more mercifully cruel than the reſt, with a Fullers Club beat out his Brains: Thus dyed this good man, in the <hi>Nintyeth</hi> year of his Age, and about <hi>Twenty four</hi> years after Chriſts Aſcenſion; being taken away, to the great grief and regret of all good men; yea, of all Sober and Iuſt Perſons, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven among the <hi>Jews;</hi> he was buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon Mount <hi>Olivet</hi> in a Tombe which he had built for himſelf, and therein he had buried <hi>Zacharias,</hi> and Old <hi>Simeon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He was of exemplary and extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Piety, educated under the ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Rules and Inſtitutions of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, being (as is ſuppoſed) of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:44102:51"/>Order of the <hi>Rechabites.</hi> Prayer was his conſtant buſineſs and delight; he ſeemed to live upon it, and to trade in nothing but the frequent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns of Converſe with Heaven: and was therefore wont to retire alone to the Temple to pray, which he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes performed kneeling, and with the greateſt Reverence, till by his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion his knees were become as hard and brawny as a <hi>Camels.</hi> Nor was his Charity towards Man, leſs than his Piety towards God; he did good to all, watched over mens Souls, and ſtudied to advance their eternal intereſt: He was of a meek and humble temper; honouring what was excellent in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, concealing what was valuable in himſelf: His Temperance was admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, he wholly abſtained from Fleſh, nor drank neither Wine nor ſtrong Drink: His holy and mortified mind was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with the meaneſt accommodati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; he went barefoot, and never wore other than Linnen Garments.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:44102:51"/>
He wrote only one Epiſtle probably not long before his Martyrdom; he directed it to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Converts, diſperſed up and down thoſe Eaſtern Countries, to comfort them under Sufferings, and to confirm them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Error.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:44102:52"/>
            <head>The Life of <hi>SIMON</hi> the Zealot.</head>
            <figure>
               <p>
                  <hi>S: SIMON</hi>
               </p>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>ST. Simon</hi> the Apoſtle was, as ſome think, one of the four Brothers of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> Sons of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> by
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:44102:52"/>his former Marriage. In the Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>gue of the Apoſtles, he is ſtyled <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on</hi> the <hi>Cananite:</hi> as alſo <hi>Simon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>elotes,</hi> or the <hi>Zealot,</hi> probably from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s warm active temper, and Zealous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rwardneſs in ſome particular way <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd profeſſion of Religion, before his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oming to our Saviour. But that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e may the better underſtand this we muſt know, that there was a diſtinct ſect among the <hi>Jewes,</hi> called, the ſect of the <hi>Zealors;</hi> they were mighty aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertors of the honour of the Law, and of the ſtrictneſs and purity of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; inſomuch, that they took upon themſelves to queſtion notorious Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders, without ſtaying for the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Formalities of the Law; yea, when the caſe required executing Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital vengeance upon them, till at length, their Zeal degenerating unto all manner of licenciouſneſs and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagance, that they not only became the peſts of the Common-Wealth at home, but opened a door for the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> to break in upon them, to their
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:44102:53"/>final and irrecoverable ruine. The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were continually prompting the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to throw off the <hi>Roman</hi> Yoak and vindicate themſelves into their Native Liberty; and when they had turned all things into hurry and confuſion, themſelves in the mean while fiſhed in theſe troubled Waters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Joſephus</hi> gives a large account of them, and every where bewailes them as the great Plague of the Nation: Nay, when <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was ſtraitly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged by the <hi>Romans,</hi> they ceaſed not to create tumults, and factions with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and were indeed the main cauſe of the <hi>Jewes</hi> ill ſucceſs in that fatal War. It is probable, that all who went un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the notion of this Sect, were not of this wretched and ungovernable temper, but that ſome of them were of a more ſober and peaceable diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition; and as it is not to be doubted, but that our <hi>Simon</hi> was of that ſect in general; ſo there is reaſon to believe he was of the better ſort. However, this makes no more reflection upon
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:44102:53"/>his being called to the Apoſtleſhip, than it did for St. <hi>Mathew,</hi> who was before a Publican, or St. <hi>Paul's</hi> being a Phariſee, and ſo Zealouſly perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Church of God.</p>
            <p>Being inveſted in the Apoſtolical Office, no further mention appears of him in the Hiſtory of the Goſpel, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining what the Apoſtles did, till their diſperſion up and down the World, he then applied himſelf to the execution of his charge. He is ſaid to have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted his Iourney towards <hi>Aegypt,</hi> thence to <hi>Cyrene</hi> and <hi>Africk,</hi> and throughout <hi>Martania,</hi> and all <hi>Lybia,</hi> Preaching the Goſpel to thoſe remote and barbarous Countries: Nor could the coldneſs of the Climate benumb his Zeal, or hinder him from Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf over into the Weſtern Iſlands, yea even to <hi>Britain</hi> it ſelf: Here he is ſaid to have Preached and wrought many Miracles, and after in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite troubles and difficulties which he underwent, ſuffered Martyrdom for the Faith of Chriſt, being Crucified
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:44102:54"/>by the Infidels, and buried among them.</p>
            <p>Others indeed affirm, that after h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had Preached the Goſpel in <hi>Aegypt</hi> he went into <hi>Meſopotamia,</hi> where h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> met with St. <hi>Jude</hi> the Apoſtle, and together with him took his Iourney in to <hi>Perſia,</hi> where having gained a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable harveſt to the Chriſtian Faith they were both Crowned with Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom: but this is granted by al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Learned Men to be fabulous, wanting all clear Foundation in Antiquity to ſtand on.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:44102:54"/>
            <head>The Life of <hi>St. JUDE.</hi>
            </head>
            <figure>
               <p>S: IUDAS</p>
               <p>THADEVS.</p>
            </figure>
            <p>THere are three ſeveral names by which this Apoſtle is deſcribed in the Hiſtory of the Goſpel, <hi>Jude, Thad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deus,</hi>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:44102:55"/>and <hi>Lebbeus.</hi> It being uſual in the Holy Volumes for the ſame Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to have more Proper Names than one; as for the firſt, it was a name common among the <hi>Jewes,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended to them, as being the name of one of the great Patriarks of their Nation. This name he ſeems afterwards to have changed for <hi>Thadde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> a word of the very ſame import and ſignification, as ſome think from a particular diſlike of the Name of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal</hi> among the Apoſtles, the bloody and Treaſonable practices of <hi>Judas Iſcariot,</hi> having rendred that name very odious and deteſtable to them; wherefore to put a difference, he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſtyles himſelf, <hi>Judas the Brother of James;</hi> for his name <hi>Lebbeus</hi> it ſeems to have been derived from an <hi>Hebrew</hi> word, ſignifying a <hi>Lyon,</hi> and therein to have reſpect to old <hi>Jacobs</hi> Propheſie, <hi>That he ſhould be as a Lyon,</hi> which probably might have a main ſtroke to faſten this name up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on St. <hi>Jude.</hi> From this Patriarchal
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:44102:55"/>Propheſie we are told, that one of the Schooles of Learned men among the <hi>Jews,</hi> took occaſion to denominate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>Labij,</hi> as accounting themſelves the Schollars and Deſcendants of this Lyon like Son of <hi>Jacob;</hi> and that St. <hi>Jude</hi> was of this Society, and becauſe of his Eminency among them retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Title of <hi>Labius,</hi> or as it was corruptly pronounced <hi>Lebbeus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For his deſcent and Parentage, he was of our Lords Kindred, the Son of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> and the Brother of <hi>James</hi> the Leſs. We find not when he was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to the Diſcipleſhip, not meeting with him, till we find him enumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted among the Catalogue of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, nor is any thing particularly recorded of him afterward, more than one queſtion that he propounded to our Saviour: Who having told them what great things he and his Father would do, and what particular mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtations, after his Reſurrection, he would make of himſelf to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and followers; St. <hi>Jude</hi> (whoſe
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:44102:56"/>thoughts, as well as the reſt, were taken up with the expectation of a Temporal Kingdom of the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi>) not knowing how that could conſiſt with the Publick Solemnity of that Glorious State they looked for: ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them what was the reaſon, that he would manifeſt himſelf to them, and not to the World. Our Lord replied, <hi>That the World were not capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of thoſe Divine Manifeſtations, as being a Stranger, and an Enemy to what ſhould fit them for Heaven; that they were only good Men, Perſons of a Divine temper of Mind, and Religious Obſervers of his Lawes, and will, whom God would honour with theſe familiar Converſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euſebius</hi> faith expreſly, That ſoon after our Lords Aſcenſion, <hi>St. Thomas</hi> diſpatched <hi>Thaddeus</hi> the Apoſtle to <hi>Abgarius</hi> Governour of <hi>Ideſſa,</hi> where he healed diſeaſes, wrought Miracles, expounded the Doctrine of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and Converted <hi>Abgarus</hi> and his People to the Faith; for all which
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:44102:56"/>pains when he offered him vaſt gifts and preſents, he refuſed them with a noble ſcorn, telling him, <hi>They had little reaſon to receive from others, what they had relinquiſhed themſelves.</hi> Here he is ſaid to have died peaceably, and to have been moſt Honourably Buried. But by the general conſent of the Latin Church, He is ſaid to have Travelled to <hi>Perſia,</hi> where, after great ſucceſs in his Apoſtolical Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry for many years, he was at laſt, for his free and open reproving the ſuperſtitious rites and uſages of the <hi>Magi,</hi> cruelly put to death.</p>
            <p>That he was one of the Marryed Apoſtles, appears ſufficiently from his Grand-Sons mentioned by <hi>Fuſebius,</hi> of whom one gives this account. <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> the Emperour, whoſe heinous Wickedneſs had awakened in him the quickeſt Iealouſies, and made him ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect every one that looked like a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival in the Empire, had heard that there were ſome of the Line of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> and <hi>Chriſts</hi> Kindred that did yet
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:44102:57"/>remain, Two Grand-Children of <hi>St. Jude,</hi> the Brother of Our Lord, were brought before him, having confeſſed, that they were of the Family and race of <hi>David,</hi> he asked them, what Poſſeſſions and Eſtates they had. They told him, that they had but a very few Acres of Land; out of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement thereof, they both payed him Tribute, and maintained them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with their own hard Labour, as by the hardneſs and brawnineſs of their hands (which then they ſhewed him) did appear. He then enquired of them concerning <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the State of his Kingdom, what kind of Empire it was, and when and where it would commence. To which they reply'd, <hi>That his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom was not of this World, nor of the Seiginories and Dominions of it; but Heavenly and Angelical, and would finally take place at the end of the World; when coming with great Glory, he would Judg the quick and the dead, and reward every one accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:44102:57"/>to their deeds.</hi> At length looking upon the meanneſs and ſimplicity of the men, as below his Iealouſies and Fears, He diſmiſſed them without uſing any ſeverities againſt them; who being now looked on, not only as Kinſmen, but as Martyrs of Our Lord, were honoured by all, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to great places of Authority, amongſt the Chriſtians, and lived till the time of <hi>Trajan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>St. Jude</hi> left only one Epiſtle of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick and Vniverſal Concernment, inſcribed at large to all Chriſtians; It was ſome time before it met with a general reception in the Church, or was taken notice of. The Author indeed ſtiles not himſelf an Apoſtle, no more doth <hi>St. James, St. John,</hi> nor ſometimes <hi>St. Paul</hi> himſelf, and why ſhould he fair the worſe, for calling himſelf <hi>The Servant of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> when he might have added, <hi>not only an Apoſtle, but Brother of our Lord?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:44102:58"/>
Being ſatisfied in the Canonical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this Epiſtle, none but <hi>St. Jude</hi> could be the Author of it, for who but he could be the Brother of <hi>St. James,</hi> a Character by which he is deſcribed in the Evangelical ſtory more than once. A Modern Writer indeed will needs have it Written by a yunger <hi>Jude,</hi> the Fifteenth Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in the reign of <hi>Adrian.</hi> And finding that that paſſage <hi>(the Brother of James,)</hi> ſtood full in his way; He concludes (but without any reaſon) that it was added by ſome Tranſcriber. But this is too bold dealing with ſacred things, no wiſe to be allowed. The deſign of the Epiſtle is to preſerve the Chriſtians from being infected by the Doctrine of the <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> the Looſe and Debauched Principles ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> and his follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, whoſe wretched Doctrines and Practices, he briefly and elegantly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents, perſwading Chriſtians hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily to avoid theſe pernicious Sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:44102:58"/>as peſts and Firebeands, not to communicate with them in their ſins, leſt they periſhed with them in that terrible vengeance that was ready to overtake them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:44102:59"/>
            <head>The Life of <hi>St. Matthias.</hi>
            </head>
            <figure>
               <p>
                  <hi>S: MATHIAS</hi>
               </p>
            </figure>
            <p>PArticular Remarks concerning St. <hi>Matthias,</hi> are not to be expected from the Hiſtory of the Goſpel, he
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:44102:59"/>not being an Apoſtle of the firſt electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. He was one of our Lords Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples (and probably one of the Seventy) that had attended upon him the whole time of his Publick Miniſtry, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Death, was Elected unto the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtleſhip, upon this occaſion: <hi>Judas Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cariot</hi> who had been one of the Twelve immediately called by <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be one of his intimate Diſciples, equally im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powered and commiſſioned with the reſt to Preach and Work Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and yet all this while, was a Man of Vile and Corrupt deſignes, branded with no meaner Character, than <hi>Thief</hi> and <hi>Murtherer,</hi> proſtituting Religion, and the Honour of his place to Covetouſneſs and evil Acts; This Covetous temper betrayed him, as in the Iſſue to the moſt fatal end; ſo to the moſt prodigious impiety that ever the Sun ſhone on, The betraying his innocent Lord, into the Hands of his cruel Enemies; but afterward awak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the horrour of the Fact, his
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:44102:60"/>Conſcience began to rouſe and follow ſo cloſe, that he was not able to bear up, under the furious revenges of his own mind never reſted till he had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched himſelf by a violent death: A vacancy being thus made in the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Apoſties, the firſt thing they did after their return from <hi>Mount O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livet,</hi> (where our Lord took his leave of them to go to St. <hi>Johns</hi> Houſe in <hi>Mount Zion</hi>) was to fill up the number with a fit proper Perſon; two were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded in order to the choice, <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> called <hi>Barſabas,</hi> and <hi>Matthias;</hi> the way of Election was by Lots, a way frequently uſed amongſt <hi>Jewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> in doubtful and difficult ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: The Lots being put in, the now <hi>Matthias</hi> his Name was drawn out, and thereby inſtalled in the Apoſtolick Office and Dignity.</p>
            <p>Not long after, the promiſed pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Holy Ghoſt were confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red upon the Apoſtles, to fit them for that great and difficult Imployment, upon which they were ſent, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:44102:60"/>the reſt, St. <hi>Matthias</hi> betook <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>imſelf to his Charge and Province. The firſt Fruits of his Miniſtery he ſpent in <hi>Judea,</hi> where having reaped a conſiderable harveſt, he betook him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to other Provinces. One tells us, that he Preached the Goſpel in <hi>Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donia,</hi> where the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> to make an experiment of his Faith and Integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, gave him a poyſonous and intoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating Potion, which he chearfully drank off in the Name of Chriſt, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt prejudice to himſelf; and that then the ſame Potion had depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved an hundred and fifty of theſe ſight, he laying his hands upon them, reſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them to their ſight again.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Greeks,</hi> with more probability, report him to have travelled <hi>Eaſtward.</hi> He came, ſaies one, to the firſt; ſaies another, to the ſecond, <hi>Ethiopia.</hi> The place whether he came, was very Wild and Barbatous, and his uſage was accordingly: For here meeting with a People of a fierce and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractible temper, he was treated by
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:44102:61"/>them with great rudeneſs and inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity; from whom, after all his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and Sufferings, and a nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Converſion of Men to Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; he obtained at laſt the Crown of Martyrdom, in the ſixty firſt year of our Lord; or as others, the ſixty fourth.</p>
            <p>Little certainty can be retrieved con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the manner of his death: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Writer of great note, tells us, That he died at a place call'd <hi>Sebaſtople,</hi> and that he was buried near the Temple of the <hi>Sun.</hi> Another reports him to have been ſeized by the <hi>Jewes,</hi> and as a Blaſphemer, to have been firſt ſton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and then beheaded. But the <hi>Greeks</hi> ſeconded herein by many antiquaries, tells us, That he was Crucified, and that as <hi>Judas</hi> was hanged upon a Tree, ſo <hi>Matthias</hi> ſuffered upon a Croſs; his body is ſaid to have been kept a long time at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> thence thought, by <hi>Helene</hi> the Mother of the great <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> to have been Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to <hi>Rome,</hi> where ſome parts of it
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:44102:61"/>are ſhewed with great Veneration this day; though others, with as great eagerneſs contend, that his Relicks were brought to, and are ſtill preſerved at <hi>Triers</hi> in <hi>Germany.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His memory is celebrated in the <hi>Greek</hi> Churches, <hi>Auguſt</hi> the <hi>Ninth;</hi> which appears not only from their <hi>Calendars,</hi> but from a Novel Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of <hi>Comnenus,</hi> appointing what holy dayes ſhould be kept in the Church. But the Weſtern Churches kept the twenty-fourth of <hi>February</hi> ſacred to his memory, among many other Apocriphal Writings attributed to the Apoſtles, where was a Goſpel Publiſhed under St. <hi>Matthias</hi> his Name, mentioned by <hi>Euſebius,</hi> and condemned with the reſt, by <hi>Golaſius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome:</hi> as it had been rejected by others before him: under his name alſo there were extant traditions cited by <hi>Clemens</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> from whence, no queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it was, that the <hi>Nicolaitans</hi> bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed that ſaying of his, which they abuſed to ſo vile and beaſtly purpoſes,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:44102:62"/>as under the pretended Patronage of his Name and Doctrine, the <hi>Marci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onites</hi> and <hi>Valentinians</hi> defended ſome of their moſt abſurd and impious Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="111" facs="tcp:44102:62"/>
            <head>The Life of St MARK <hi>the Evangeliſt,</hi>
            </head>
            <figure>
               <p>S: MARKE</p>
            </figure>
            <p>THough this great Evangeliſt car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſomething of <hi>Roman</hi> in his Name, without all queſtion born of
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:44102:63"/>
               <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Parents, Originally deſcended of the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> and the Prieſtly Line, and (if ſome of the Antients miſtake not) Siſters Son to <hi>Peter;</hi> though others, without any ſhadow of reaſon, have confounded him with <hi>John</hi> Sirnamed <hi>Mark,</hi> the Son of <hi>Mary,</hi> and <hi>Mark's</hi> Siſters Son to <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas.</hi> The particular reaſon of his changing his Name from <hi>Jewiſh</hi> to <hi>Roman,</hi> is not clear from Hiſtory; yet it is moſt probable, that he aſſumed the <hi>Roman</hi> Name <hi>Mark,</hi> upon ſome great change or accident of his Life; or (which was not unuſual among the <hi>Jewes,</hi> then going to the <hi>European</hi> Provinces of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire) ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up at his going for <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the Antients, he is generally thought to have been one of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty Diſciples; and ſome of them poſitively affirm, that he was one of them, who taking exceptions at our Saviours diſcourſe of <hi>Eating his Fleſh, and Drinking his Blood,</hi> went back,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:44102:63"/>and walked no more with him, but was ſeaſonably reduced and reclaimed by <hi>Peter;</hi> but others as confidently, and with as great Reaſon affirm, That he was no Hearer, nor Follower of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and therefore could be none of them, who, upon that occaſion, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook him. He was Converted by ſome of the Apoſtles, and probably by <hi>St. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> who calls him his Son; from which ſome conclude, That <hi>Peter</hi> was his undertaker at his Baptiſm. He was indeed his conſtant Attendant and Follower all along in his Travels, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying the place of an <hi>Amanuenſis</hi> and Interpreter. For though the Apoſtles were divinely Inſpired; and among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther miraculous Powers, had the gift of Languages conferred upon them; yet were the Interpretation of Tongues a Gift more peculiar to ſome than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; this might probably be <hi>St. Mark's</hi> Talent, in expounding <hi>St. Peter's</hi> Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes in word or writing, to thoſe who underſtood not the Language wherein they were delivered. He ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:44102:64"/>him in his Apoſtolical pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs, Preached the Goſpel in <hi>Italy,</hi> and at <hi>Rome,</hi> where, at the requeſt of the Chriſtians in thoſe parts, he Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed his Goſpel. By St. <hi>Peter</hi> he was ſent to <hi>Aegypt,</hi> to plant Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in that Country. He fixed his main Reſidence at <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and the places thereabouts, for a conſiderable time, where ſo great (as one of the Ancients writes) was the Succeſs of his Miniſtry, that he Converted vaſt Multitudes, both of Men and Women, of all ranks and degrees, not only to the imbracing the Chriſtian Faith, but to a more than ordinary ſtrict Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of it: Inſomuch, that <hi>Philo</hi> the <hi>Jew</hi> wrote a Book, which treats only of their particular. Rites, and way of Life; for which reaſons, one of the Fathers reckons him among the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Church. <hi>Philo</hi> did indeed write a Book, which is extant to this day, wherein he Treats of a ſort of People, who (in many parts of the World, but eſpecially in a pleaſant
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:44102:64"/>place Scituated upon the <hi>Mardolick Lake</hi> in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> had formed themſelves into Religious Societies, and gives a large Account of their Rites and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, their ſtrict phyloſophical and contemplative Courſe of Life: He fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tells us, That when they did firſt enter upon this courſe of Life, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced all ſecular Intereſts and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, and leaving their Eſtates to their Friends, retired into Groves and Gardens, and places devoted to Retirement and Contemplation; that they had their Houſes or Colledges, not contigious, that ſo being free from noiſe and tumults, and ſuch like incumbrances, they might the better miniſter to the Deſign of a contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plative Life; nor yet removed at too great a diſtance, that they might main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain mutual Society, and be conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently capable of helping and aſſiſting one another, as their need required: in the middle of theſe Houſes, there was an Oratory, wherein they diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the more ſecret and ſolenm parts
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:44102:65"/>of their Religion, divided in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, by a partition Wall, three or four Cubits high; the one Appartment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the Men, the other for the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Here they publickly met every Seventh Day, where being ſet accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their Seniority, and compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing themſelves with great Decency and Reverence, the moſt aged Perſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, and the beſt skilled in the Precepts and Principles of their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, came forth into the midſt, gravely and ſoverly Diſcourſing of what might make the deepeſt Impreſſion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Minds; the reſt attending with a profound Silence; and only teſtifying their Aſſent with the motion of their Eyes or Head: They were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo very careleſs of their Bodyes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wholly taken up with Religious Contemplations; they ſpent the Day entirely in Divine Meditations, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther exerciſes of Devotion; they were alſo exceeding temperate, neither eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nor drinking till Night. Any that would be further Satisfied about this
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:44102:65"/>People, let them peruſe a book writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by <hi>Philo</hi> the <hi>Jew,</hi> concerning them, which is extant to this Day.</p>
            <p>Some of the Ancients have peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily affirmed, That thoſe excellent Perſons were indeed Chriſtians, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted and brought under theſe admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Rules of a ſtrict Converſation, by the Life and Doctrine of St. <hi>Mark,</hi> at his coming hither; but yet <hi>Philo's</hi> Account of them, being ſeriouſly weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it will be found, he meant it of <hi>Jews,</hi> and not Chriſtians; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, it ſeems not probable, that he being a <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Hiſtorian, would give ſuch a great Character, and Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation to Chriſtians, who were ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hateful to the <hi>Jews</hi> over all the World; yea, further this Author ſpeaks of this Inſtitution, to have been ſome conſiderable ſtanding, and therefore cannot take them for Chriſtians; Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity being at that time even in the Bud, by means of St. <hi>Mark's</hi> mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry.</p>
            <p>Theſe, who took them for Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:44102:66"/>might eaſily be led into this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, by obſerving the Conformity that was between the Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, who entred upon a more ſtrict and ſevere courſe of Life: and theſe <hi>Therapeutae,</hi> an ordinary Fancy being able to draw a fair Parallel between them; and ſo it was, but removing them ſome Ages higher, and imagining them to have been Converted and Founded by St. <hi>Mark<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and the Work was done. Indeed it is not to be doubted, but that Perſons educated under theſe excellent Rules and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of Life, were more than ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily prepared for the reception of Chriſtianity, between which, and their Principles, and Rules of Life, there was ſo great an Affinity and Agreement, which muſt needs render our Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts Succeſs great in thoſe parts, and open the way for men to come flocking over to the Faith. St. <hi>Mark</hi> did not confine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> his Miniſtry to <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and the Oriential parts of <hi>Aegypt</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but removed <hi>Weſt</hi>-ward to the parts
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:44102:66"/>of <hi>Libia,</hi> going through the Countrys of <hi>Marmarica</hi> and <hi>Pentapelis,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers thereabouts, where, though the people were both Barbarous in their Manners, and Idolatrous in their Worſhip, yet by his Preaching and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, he made way for the entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Goſpel, and left them not till he had not only gained them to, hut alſo confirmed them in the Profeſſion of it. Returning to <hi>Alexandria,</hi> he Preached freely, and ordered, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed the Affairs of the Church, and wiſely provided for Succeſſion by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituting Governours and Paſtors of it: but the reffleſs Enemies of the Souls of men, would not ſufter him long to live in quiet.</p>
            <p>All was at the time of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> at the time the great Solemnities of <hi>Serapis,</hi> hapned to be Celebrated; When the Minds of the people being Paſſionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Excited to a Vindication of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of their <hi>Idol,</hi> broke in upon St. <hi>Mark</hi> when ingaged in the Solemn Celebration of divine Worſhip, and
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:44102:67"/>binding his feet with Cords, dragged him through the ſtreets, and moſt craggy and ſtony places, to the <hi>Bouc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clus,</hi> a Precipice near the Sea; and for that night thruſt him into Priſon, where his Soul was by a Divine Viſion, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected and encouraged under the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines of his ſhattered Body. Early the next morning, theſe bloudy hounds be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to Act their fatal tragedy; again, dragging him about in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, till his Fleſh being raked off, and his Blood run out in great Streams, all the way whereever they drew him; his Spirits failed him, and he Expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. But their Mallice ended not with his dayes; For a Father of very much Reſpect, Adds, That when he was Dead, they burnt his Body into Aſhes; which Aſhes the Chriſtians carefully gathered together, and decently Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, near the place where he was wont to Preach. Afterwards it was with great Splendor removed from <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria</hi> to <hi>Venice,</hi> where it now lies Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and is Religiouſly Honoured by
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:44102:67"/>the Inhabitants. <hi>St. Mark</hi> being A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopted to be the Tutelar Saint of that State, where he hath one of the ſtatelieſt, and moſt Magnificent Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Erected in honour of his Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that the Univerſal World can boaſt of at this day.</p>
            <p>He ſuffered Martyrdom upon the five and twentieth of <hi>April,</hi> though the certain year of his Sufferings is not preciſely agreed upon by the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents. Some ſay, it was in the laſt year of the Emperor <hi>Claudius;</hi> others, place it in the eighth year of <hi>Nero.</hi> But another ſeemes extravagantly wide, where with great confidence Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, That he ſuffered in the time of <hi>Trajan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Among all theſe various conjectures, that which ſeems moſt probable, and carries moſt appearance of reaſon, with it, is, That this Holy Man ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about the end of <hi>Neroes</hi> Reign: For ſuppoſing him to have come to <hi>Rome</hi> with St. <hi>Peter,</hi> about the fifth or ſixth Year of <hi>Nero;</hi> he might thence
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:44102:68"/>be diſpatched to <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and ſpend the reſidue of his Life, and of that Emperours Reign, in Planting Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity in thoſe parts of the World. For it is beyond all debate, that <hi>Irineus</hi> affirmeth St. <hi>Mark,</hi> to have out-lived both St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and after their deceaſe to have compoſed his Goſpel, out of thoſe things which he formerly had heard St. <hi>Peter</hi> Preach; nay, in many other paſſages of this Father's Writings, he ſuppoſed (whoſe Suppoſition certainly was not founded upon meer fancy and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture) that St. <hi>Mark</hi> for ſome conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable time ſurvived the Martyrdom of thoſe two great Apoſtles. As to the Perſon of this great Evangeliſt, it may not be impertinent to trouble the Reader with a few words concerning it, taken from the ſame Authorities, from which we have borrowed the reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of his Life and Actions. As to his Perſon, he was of a middle ſize and Stature, of a comely and well propor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tioned body, and a wholeſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution;
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:44102:68"/>his Noſe long, his eye-brows turning back; his Eyes full of graceful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs &amp; amiableneſs; his Head, by reaſon of this great Age, very bald, his Beard long and Gray, his gate quick: in a word, he was indued with all the deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable qualities of a lovely Perſon.</p>
            <p>His Goſpel was, (as we obſerd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed above) written at the requeſt of the Converts at <hi>Rome,</hi> who, not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to have heard <hi>Peter</hi> Preach, preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed St. <hi>Mark<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> his Fellow-Labourer, to commit to Writing an account of theſe things which he Preached to them, &amp; that by way of Hiſtory; which he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed with exceeding great faithfulneſs and brevity, all which St. <hi>Peter</hi> peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and ratified with his Apoſtolical Authority, commanding it to be owned &amp; preſerved with the reſt of the Canonical Books of the Scripture. And though ſome of the Fathers ſeemed inclinable to think it was Written after St. <hi>Peters</hi> Death; yet all that can be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred from thence (taking it for truth) will be, that in it ſelf, is a matter of
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:44102:69"/>no great moment and importance, that the Ancients were not fully agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the exact time, when every particular Book of the Goſpel were Publiſhed to the World. Some have been at great pains to prove the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, not to have been St. <hi>Marks,</hi> but St. <hi>Peters;</hi> ſomtimes running to the Fathers, and finding no ſhelter there, they recur to Polemical debates of latter times, wherein they have ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more wit and ſharpneſs, than in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity and honeſty. It is true, it was frequently ſtiled St. <hi>Peters</hi> Goſpel, not ſo much becauſe dictated by him to St. <hi>Mark,</hi> as becauſe he principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly compoſed it of that account, which St. <hi>Peter</hi> uſually delivered in his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes to the People; which proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly is the reaſon, why a Learned Man doth obſerve, that he in his ſtile and manner of expreſſion, delights to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate St. <hi>Peter</hi> repreſenting very much in a few words: This obſervation, though bold in ſome things, yet not in all; for though St. <hi>Matthew</hi> is larger in giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:44102:69"/>the account of our Saviours Life, than he; yet in many places, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces the ſtory into a narrower com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs than St. <hi>Mark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Laſt Chapter of his Goſpel (as St. <hi>Jerome</hi> informs us) at leaſt a part of it was wanting in all the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient <hi>Greek</hi> Copies, being rejected, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account of a pretended diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement with the other Goſpels, though as this Father himſelf, there ſhews, they are very fairly conſiſtent one with another; nor is there any diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in any paſſage of them. His great impartiality in his Relation doth moſt clearly appear from hence, that he is ſo far from concealing or alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viating the ſhameful lapſe, and denial of <hi>Peter</hi> his dear Tutor and Maſter, to whom he was ſo deeply ingaged in the bonds of Love; that he ſets it down with ſome particular weighty Circumſtances, and Aggravations; which the other <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> thought ſit (for reaſons known to themſelves)
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:44102:70"/>though they could not but know it) to take no notice of it. Some diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute has been made (and kept on foot in the Church) in what Language this Goſpel was Written; ſome affirm it to have been Written in the <hi>Latin</hi> Tongue Originally: that which ſeems to give moſt Countenance to this, is a Note which we find at the end of the <hi>Syriack</hi> Verſion of this Goſpel; where it is ſaid, That St. <hi>Mark</hi> Preached and Publiſhed his Holy Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel at <hi>Rome,</hi> in the <hi>Roman</hi> or <hi>Latine</hi> Tongue. An Evidence that would un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtly carry the force of a Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration with all reaſonable men, were they aſſured, that this Note is of equal Value and Authority with that ancient Verſion, generally ſuppoſed to come very few Centuries ſhort of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick Age. Beſides, theſe <hi>Jews,</hi> which heard <hi>St. Mark</hi> preach, being but ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers at <hi>Rome,</hi> could underſtand but very little <hi>Latine;</hi> but upon the other hand, the <hi>Roman</hi> Converts could not
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:44102:70"/>but underſtand <hi>Greek,</hi> it being at that time the moſt faſhionable and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicative Language in the World; nor can any good Reaſon be aſſigned, why it ſhould be more inconvenient for <hi>St. Mark,</hi> to write his Goſpel in <hi>Greek</hi> for the uſe of the <hi>Romans,</hi> than that <hi>St. Paul</hi> ſhould, in that very Language, write his Epiſtle to the Church.</p>
            <p>The Original <hi>Greek</hi> Copy written, with <hi>St. Mark's</hi> own hand, is ſaid to be extant at <hi>Venice</hi> at this Day. Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, as ſome Inform us, by him at <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quileja,</hi> and thence, after many Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of Years, Tranſlated to <hi>Venice,</hi> where it is ſtill preſerved to this very day, an ancient Monument, and worth keeping. The Letters of it are ſo worn out with length of time, that ſuch, as to ſatisfy their Curioſity, obtain a ſight of it are not capable to read a Sentence of it to purpoſe, though ſome words appear here and there in ſome parts of it; in others, nothing but a few Letters and Characters: ſo
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:44102:71"/>that this Generation is not a compleat judge of its Authentickneſs; not being capable, either to approve or diſapprove it; but it being of no great weight, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be the Original or not, it is not worth contending for.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="129" facs="tcp:44102:71"/>
            <head>The Life of St. LUKE <hi>the Evangeliſt,</hi>
            </head>
            <figure>
               <p>
                  <hi>S:</hi> LUKE</p>
            </figure>
            <p>SAint <hi>Luke</hi> was born at <hi>Antioch</hi> the Metropolis of <hi>Syria,</hi> a City celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for its extraordinary bleſſings and
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:44102:72"/>eminencies; the pleaſantneſs of its Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuation, the fertility of its Soil, the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of its Traffick, the wiſdom of its Senare, the learning of its Profeſſors, the civility and politeneſs of its Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, by the pens of ſome of the moſt eloquent of their time: and yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all theſe, renowned for this one pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar honour, That here it was, that the Diſciples were firſt called Chriſtians. It was an Vniverſity repleniſhed with Schooles of learning; wherein were profeſſors of all Arts and Sciences, ſo that this Evangeliſt being born in the very lap of the Muſes, he could not miſs of a liberal &amp; ingenious Education; his natural parts meeting with the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of great improvement. Nay, we are told by ſome, that he ſtudied not only at <hi>Antioch,</hi> but at moſt Schooles both of <hi>Greece</hi> and <hi>Aegypt,</hi> whereby he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came learned in all parts of Learning &amp; humane Sciences. Being thus furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out with Skill, in all the preparato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry inſtitutions of Phyloſophy; he more particularly applyed himſelf to the ſtudy
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:44102:72"/>of Phyſick, for which the Grecian Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies were moſt famous. Hence ſome conclude him to have been of high birth &amp; noble blood but their miſtake is found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon their not conſidering, that this noble act was in theſe times profeſsed generally by ſuch as were of no higher value then that of Servants: upon which account, a learned man conceives that St. <hi>Luke,</hi> though a <hi>Syrian</hi> by birth, to have been a ſervant at <hi>Rome,</hi> where he ſomtimes practiſed Phyſick; and being ſent from thence, returned to his own Country: there probably he continued his Profeſſion all the dayes of his life; it being fairly conſiſtent with, and in many caſes ſubſervient to the work of the Miniſtery, and the care of ſouls. Beſides, his knowledge in Phyſick, he is ſaid to have been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert in the art of Painting; and there are no leſs than three or four pieces of Painting ſtill in being, ſaid to have been of his drawing. There is alſo an antient Inſcription to be ſeen in the <hi>Via Lactea</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> in an old Vault
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:44102:73"/>near the Church of St. <hi>Mary,</hi> ſuppoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have been the place where St. <hi>Paul</hi> dwelt; wherein mention is made of the Picture of the Bleſſed Virgin, <hi>Being one of the Seven Painted by St.</hi> Luke.</p>
            <p>He was a Iewiſh Proſelite; <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>och</hi> abounding with Men of that Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who had their Synagogues and Schooles of Education; ſo that we need not, as ſome do, ſend him to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to be inſtructed in the Law. As for the Opinon of ſome great Men, That he was one of them who had ſhamefully forſaken his Lord &amp; Maſter, for the unwelcome diſcourſe he made to the People, and was reclaimed again by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> being alſo by them ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to have been one of the ſeventy Diſciples; it ſeems to be no other than a meer fiction; upon no better ground is it ſaid, <hi>That he was one of the Two Diſciples who were going to</hi> Emaus, <hi>to whom the Lord appeared in their way.</hi> For beſides other Arguments which might be brought to evince the
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:44102:73"/>contrary to both, he himſelf confeſſeth plainly, <hi>That he was not from the Begining an eye Witneſs and Miniſter of the Word.</hi> It is therefore moſt probable, that he was converted by St. <hi>Paul</hi> during his abode at <hi>Antioch,</hi> when as the Apoſtles were of Catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Fiſh, become Fiſhers of Men; ſo he of a Phyſitian for the Body, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a Phyſitian for the Soul.</p>
            <p>Some of the Antients will have this to have been done at <hi>Thebes,</hi> the Chief City of <hi>Baeotia</hi> about fourty Miles diſtance from <hi>Athens;</hi> but this ſeems to have a bad Foundation, for it doth not appear from any credible Author of that time, that ever St. <hi>Paul</hi> was at <hi>Thebes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He became ever after his inſeparable Companion, and Fellow-Labourer in the Work of the Miniſtry, eſpecially after his going into <hi>Macedonia;</hi> from which time, in Recording the Hiſtory of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Travels, he alwayes (as occaſion ſerves) ſpeaketh of himſelf in his own Perſon. He atteneded St.
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:44102:74"/>
               <hi>Paul</hi> in all his dangers, was with him at his ſeveral Arraignments at <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> accompanied him in his moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and deſperate Voyage to <hi>Rome,</hi> where he moſt conſtantly attended upon him, to ſerve his neceſſaries, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply thoſe Miniſterial Offices, which the Apoſtles confinement, would not ſuffer him to undergo, eſpecially in carrying meſſages to thoſe Churches, wherein he had planted Chriſtianity: This infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely indeared him to St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who owned him for his Fellow-Labourer, called him the Beloved Phiſitian, and the Brother, whoſe praiſe is in the Goſpel, throughout all the Churches, which the Antients, eſpecially St. <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> apply to our Evangeliſt.</p>
            <p>It is more than probable, that he did not leave St. <hi>Paul,</hi> untill that he had fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed his Courſe, and Crowned all his ſufferings with Martyrdom; though ſome aver, that he left St. <hi>Paul</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> and returned back into the Eaſt, and Travelled into <hi>Aegypt,</hi> &amp; the parts of <hi>Lybia;</hi> where he according to his
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:44102:74"/>Cuſtom Preached the Goſpel, wrought Miracles, Converted Multitudes, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Miniſters and Paſtors in the Church; yea, that he himſelf took up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him the Epiſcopal charge of the City of <hi>Thebais. Epiphanius</hi> gives us this account, That he Preached the Goſpel firſt in <hi>Dalmatia</hi> and <hi>Galatia,</hi> (by which Latter, he means <hi>Gaul</hi> or <hi>France,</hi> where, in the Iudgment of others, he is very far miſtaken) then in <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Macedonia,</hi> where he ſpared no pains, declined not the greateſt and moſt threatning dangers that he might faithfully, and with ſincerity of heart, diſcharge that great and important truſt, which was committed to him.</p>
            <p>The Antients are not very well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, either about the time, or man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of his Death and Martyrdom; ſome of them aſſuring him to have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>Aegypt;</hi> others ſay, with as great confidence, that he dyed in <hi>Greece.</hi> The <hi>Roman</hi> Martyrologie makes <hi>By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinia</hi> the place of his Martyrdom. <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rotheus</hi> is at a great deal of pains to
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:44102:75"/>prove, That all the former are in a miſtake, and that St. <hi>Luke</hi> dyed at nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the forenamed places, but that he ſuffered, and payed his vowes at <hi>Epheſus.</hi> They alſo diſagree as much as to the manner of his death, as they do as to the place. Some make him die a natural; others, a violent death. Indeed, neither <hi>Euſebius,</hi> nor St. <hi>Jerom</hi> takes any notice of it, whether becauſe they wanted a certain or true ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of it, or for ſome other reaſon beſt known to themſelves, let the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der determine. Yet <hi>Nazianzen, Paulinus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Nola,</hi> with ſeveral others, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly aſſert, That he was Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with a Crown of Martyrdom; of which <hi>Nicephorus</hi> gives this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Account: That coming to <hi>Greece,</hi> he Succeſsfully Preached and Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed many Converts into the Chriſtian Faith, that the number of Believers did daily increaſe, and every thing, wherein his Miniſtry was concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, did Succeſsfully proſper; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til, at length, the Lord thinking it
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:44102:75"/>time to call home his Servant, with his Commiſſion (having no more Work for him among the Infidels) A party of Villains made Head againſt him, and layed hold on him; where, after they had Glutted their greedy and helliſh Appetites with his Torture, they drag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged him to Execution; but when they came to the place where they intended to Perpetrate the reſt of their Villany, they could not find a Croſs to fix him upon; whereupon being reſolved, by any means, to diſpatch him, they carried him a little further, where they ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon an <hi>Olive</hi> Tree, which they thought meet for their purpoſe; upon which they Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged him the <hi>Eightyeth,</hi> ſay ſome; but others, the <hi>Eighty Fourth</hi> Year of his Age.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Kirſtenius,</hi> from an Antient <hi>Arabick</hi> Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, labours to prove, that he ſuffered Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom at <hi>Rome;</hi> which he thinks might proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be, after St. <hi>Paul's</hi> firſt Impriſonment there; when St. <hi>Luke</hi> being left behind, as his Deputy, to ſupply his place in the Work of the Miniſtry, was ſhortly after put to Death, which he thinks might be the reaſon why he did not further Proſecute the Hiſtory of the Acts of the Apoſtles; which he would un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly have done, had he Lived any conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable time after St. <hi>Paul's</hi> departure.</p>
            <p>His Body afterward, by the ſpecial com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of <hi>Conſtantine;</hi> or as others ſay, of
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:44102:76"/>his Son <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> was with great Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity removed from <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and was Buried in that great and famous Church, built and dedicated to the Memory of the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>He Wrote two Books for the uſe and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the Church; his Goſpel, and the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Acts of the Apoſtles; both which he Dedicated to <hi>Theophilus.</hi> Now it is deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted among the Ancients, what this <hi>Theophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> is, ſome conclude it to have been a feign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Name, made uſe of by St. <hi>Luke</hi> in this place, denoting no more than a Lover of God; a Title common to every Chriſtian: But o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, with more appearance of Reaſon, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude it the proper Name of a particular Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; and that which ſatisfies them abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in their Iudgment, is, That the Title and Stile of <hi>Moſt Excellent,</hi> is beſtowed upon him; which was, in thoſe times, the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Title, and proper Form of Addreſs to Princes, and great Men: Yea, ſome of the Primitive Fathers, do expreſly term him a Man of Conſular Dignity, and probably a Prince; and others are yet more particular in their Account of him, ſaying, That he was a Noble-man of <hi>Antioch,</hi> who was Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted by <hi>Peter;</hi> and who, upon his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, gave his Houſe to the Church, for the place of their publick and ſolemn Meeting.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:44102:76"/>
But it may as probably be ſuppoſed, that this <hi>Theophilus</hi> might have been ſome Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, or a Chief Man in Authority, whom St. <hi>Luke</hi> had brought in to the Faith, and Baptized; and to whom he now dedicated theſe Books, not only as a Teſtimony of honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Reſpect, but alſo as a means of giving him further Light into the certainty and aſſurance of theſe things, wherein he had been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed by him.</p>
            <p>As for his Goſpel, St. <hi>Jerome,</hi> and ſome others, ſuppoſe it to have been Written in <hi>Arabia,</hi> during his Travels with St. <hi>Paul</hi> in thoſe Parts, whoſe help he is generally ſaid to have made uſe of, in Compoſing of it; and that this the Apoſtle primarily intends, when he ſo often ſpeaks of his Goſpel; but what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Aſſiſtance the Apoſtle might contribute to the Work, it is clear, that the Evangeliſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf tells us expreſly, That he derived his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence in thoſe matters, from thoſe who had, from the Beginning, been Eye-Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Miniſters of the Word: Nor does it in the leaſt detract from the Authority of his Relation, that he himſelf was not preſent at the doing of them; for if we conſider who they were, from whom he derived his Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence of thoſe things, it may give abundant Satisfaction, he had a Stock, both of Credit and Intelligence; to proceed upon the Authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickneſs
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:44102:77"/>and Sufficiency of which, is beyond Expectation: for he delivered nothing in his whole Hiſtory, but what he had immediately recovered from Perſons preſent at, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly concerned in the things which he has left upon Record.</p>
            <p>The occaſion of his Writing his Goſpel, is conceived to have been partly, to prevent thoſe falſe and ſcandalous Rumors and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, which, even at that time, began to be obtruded upon the World; and partly to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply what was wanting in thoſe two <hi>Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts,</hi> that Wrote before him; which Supple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is particularly noted throughout the whole Hiſtory by ſome of the Primitive Fathers.</p>
            <p>The ſubject Matter of the whole Hiſtory is, an Account of what relates to <hi>Chriſt's</hi> Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Office; and though, when he Recordeth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paſſages in the Evangelical Story, he is very particular in his Relation; yet we may eaſily obſerve, that it is always with a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Reſpect to <hi>Chriſt's</hi> Preiſt-hood: upon which account the Ancients, in accommodating the four ſymbolical Repreſentments in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets Viſion, to the four Evangeliſts, aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>Oxe</hi> or <hi>Calf</hi> to St. <hi>Luke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Hiſtory of the Apoſtolick Acts, was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly written at <hi>Rome,</hi> at the end of St. <hi>Paul's</hi> two Years Impriſonment there, with which he concludes his Story: it contains the
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:44102:77"/>Actions, and ſometimes the Sufferings of ſome of the greateſt Apoſtles, but more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly of St. <hi>Paul;</hi> for beſides that his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity in the cauſe of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the Goſpel, made him have a deeper ſhare, both in doing and ſuffering; St. <hi>Luke</hi> was his conſtant Attendant, an Eye-witneſs of all the moſt famous tranſactions of his Life, after his Converſion; yea, was privy to his moſt ſecret Concerns; and therefore was capable of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a more accurat and ſatisfying Account and Relation of them, ſeeing no Evidence or Teſtimony in matters of Fact, is ſo convictive and rationally pungent, than his, who Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports nothing but what he hath heard and ſeen.</p>
            <p>Among other things, he gives a particular and exact account of thoſe great and wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Miracles, which the Apoſtles did Work, for the Confirmation of the Doctrine of the Goſpel, which they daily Preached. And this (as one of the Fathers enformeth us) was the reaſon, why, in the primitive Times, the Book of the Acts, though containing thoſe Actions of the Apoſtles, which were done af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Pentecoſt,</hi> were yet uſually read in the Church, before it, in the ſpace between that and <hi>Eaſter;</hi> when, as at all other times, thoſe parts of the Goſpel were Read, which were proper for the Seaſon: It was (ſayes he)
<pb facs="tcp:44102:78"/>becauſe the Apoſtles Miracles were the grand Confirmation of the Truth of <hi>Chriſt's</hi> Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and thoſe Miracles were Recorded in that Book; it was therefore thought moſt proper, to be Read next to the Feaſt of the Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>In both theſe Books, his way of Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting is exact and accurat, his Stile polite and elegant, ſublime and lofty; and yet clear and perſpituous, flowing with an eaſy and natural Grace and Sweetneſs, admirably accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to an Hiſtorical Deſign; all along expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing himſelf in a Vein of purer <hi>Greek,</hi> than is to be found in the other Writers of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Story: Indeed, being Born and Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at <hi>Antioch</hi> (then which no place more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for Oratory and Eloquence) he could not but carry away a great ſhare of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Genius of that place, though his Stile is ſometimes allayed with a mixture of the <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riak</hi> and <hi>Hebrew</hi> Dialect. It was obſerved of old (as St. <hi>Jerome</hi> tells us) that his Skill was greater in <hi>Greek,</hi> than in <hi>Hebrew;</hi> that therefore he always makes uſe of the <hi>Septua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gint</hi> Tranſlation, and refuſes ſometimes to render words, when the Propriety of the <hi>Greek</hi> Tongue will not bear it.</p>
            <p>To Conclude, As an Hiſtorian, he was Faithful in his Relations, Elegant in his Writings; As a Miniſter, careful and diligent
<pb facs="tcp:44102:78"/>for the good of Souls; As a Chriſtian, devout and pious: And who Crowned all the reſt, with the laying down his Life for the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of that Goſpel, which he had both Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and Publiſhed to the World.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
